<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-03T12:27:36+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Mathematic </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How do economists measure risk aversion?</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/RiskAversion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do economists measure risk aversion?"/><published>2025-10-02T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-02T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/RiskAversion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/RiskAversion/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>“Uncertainty must be taken in a sense radically distinct from the familiar notion of Risk, from which it has never been properly separated … a measurable uncertainty, or ‘risk’ proper … is so far different from an unmeasurable one that it is not in effect an uncertainty at all.” — Frank H. Knight, Risk, Uncertainty and Profit</p> </blockquote> <p>The agents in any economy face risky gambles on a daily basis. The uncertainty in the choices of the agent can lead to consequences that agent does not like. The agents relative preferences about consequences is usually abstracted out by a expected utility function (sometimes justified by von Neumann and Morgenstein’s theorem that produces an expected utility function from ordinal preferences).</p> <p>The uncertainty associated to the consequences is modelled by a probability space $(\Omega, {\cal F},P)$. The payoff of a risky gamble is denoted by a random variable $X:\Omega \to \mathbb{R}$. Suppose that the agents wealth before the gamble was offered is $w$ and the utility function associated to the agent is $u.$</p> <p>Following Pratt (in @pratt1964), in order to appreciate the risk profile of the agent, we perform the following experiment. Let $\pi$ be a real number. We offer the agent two choices:</p> <ol> <li>(Risky gamble) The agent can accept a payoff of $X$ units.</li> <li>(Risk adjusted Certain) The agent can accept a payoff $\mathbb{E}(X) - \pi$.</li> </ol> <div class="math-block"> <strong>Proposition.</strong> If \( u \) is a concave continuous increasing function then there exists a unique positive real number $\pi$ such that the agent is indifferent to the choices between a risky gamble and risk adjusted certain payoff. </div> <div class="math-block proof"> <strong>Proof.</strong> By Jensen's inequality for concave functions \(u\), \[\mathbb{E}(u\left(w+X\right)) &lt; u\left(w+\mathbb{E}(X)\right).\] Since the $u$ is continuous, there must exist a real number \(\pi\) so that \[\mathbb{E}(u\left(w+X\right)) = u\left(w+\mathbb{E}(X)-\pi\right).\] Further $\pi$ unique since the function is increasing. Thus the agent is indifferent to the choices for this \( \pi \), since the expected utilities associated to the choices are equal.∎ </div> <p>Note that $\pi &gt; 0$ means that the agent is willing to forego some amount of cash to avoid risk. We will assume that this amount depends on the wealth of the agent $w$ and the offered gamble $X$. The amount $\pi$ that makes the agent indifferent to the risky proposition is called a <em>risk premium associated to X</em>.</p> <p><em>Definition:</em> Suppose an agent with wealth $w$ and differentiable monotone utility function $u$ is offered a risky gamble $X$. The risk premium $\pi$ associated with gamble $X$ is defined as the real number that solves the equation $\mathbb{E}(u\left(w+X\right)) = u\left(w+\mathbb{E}(X)-\pi\right)$</p> <p>The proposition guarantees that a positive risk premium exists for concave utility function.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="certainty-equivalent-and-risk-premium">Certainty Equivalent and Risk Premium</h3> <div class="math-block"> <strong>Definition.</strong> The certainty equivalent associated to a risky gamble $X$ is the sure amount $c$ such that \[ u(w+c) \;=\; \mathbb{E}[u(w+X)]. \] </div> <p>The <strong>risk premium</strong> $\pi$ is then defined as the difference between the expected value of the gamble and the certainty equivalent: \(\pi \;=\; \mathbb{E}[X] - c.\)</p> <ul> <li>$\pi &gt; 0$ : risk-averse (concave $u$).</li> <li>$\pi = 0$ : risk-neutral (linear $u$).</li> <li>$\pi &lt; 0$ : risk-loving (convex $u$).</li> </ul> <div class="math-block"> <strong>Example.</strong> Suppose $X$ pays \$200 with probability $1/2$ and \$0 with probability $1/2$. Then $\mathbb{E}[X] = 100$. If the certainty equivalent is $c=80$, the risk premium is $\pi = 20$. The agent is willing to forego \$20 to avoid the risk. </div> <h3 id="local-risk-aversion">Local Risk Aversion</h3> <p>We will now compute the risk premium that a risk-averse agent is willing to pay for an <em>infinitesimal</em> gamble. This means that the payoff from the gamble is really negligible compared to the agent’s wealth.</p> <p>Instead of messing with a payoff, we will allow the agent to choose a fraction $t$ of the gamble’s payoff and compute the risk premium $\pi(t)$. Let $X$ be a mean-zero gamble, $\mathrm{Var}(X)=\sigma^2&lt;\infty$. For each scale $t&gt;0$, define the risk premium $\pi(t)$ by the certainty-equivalence condition $u(x-\pi(t)) \;=\; \mathbb{E}[u(x+tX)].$</p> <p>Local risk aversion is the coefficient that links the <strong>second-order</strong> cost of small risk to its variance.</p> <div class="math-block"> <strong>Proposition (Local risk premium and Arrow–Pratt index).</strong> Suppose \(u\in C^3\) with \(u'(x)&gt;0\). Let \(X\) satisfy \(\mathbb{E}[X]=0\), \(\mathbb{E}[X^2]=\sigma^2&lt;\infty\). Then, as \(t\to 0\), \[ \pi(t)\;=\;\tfrac{1}{2}\,r(x)\,\sigma^2\,t^2 \;+\; o(t^2), \qquad\text{where}\qquad r(x)\;:=\;-\frac{u''(x)}{u'(x)}. \] Moreover, \(r(x)\) is invariant under positive affine transformations of utility (if \(\tilde u= a u + b\), \(a&gt;0\), then \(-\tilde u''/\tilde u' = -u''/u'\)). </div> <div class="math-block proof"> <strong>Proof.</strong> Taylor expand the left side around \(x\): \[ u(x-\pi)=u(x)-u'(x)\pi+\tfrac12 u''(x)\pi^2+O(\pi^3). \] Taylor expand the right side inside expectation: \[ u(x+tX)=u(x)+u'(x)tX+\tfrac12 u''(x)t^2X^2+O(t^3|X|^3). \] Taking expectations and using \(\mathbb{E}[X]=0\), \(\mathbb{E}[X^2]=\sigma^2\), \[ \mathbb{E}[u(x+tX)] = u(x) + \tfrac12 u''(x)\sigma^2 t^2 + O(t^3\,\mathbb{E}|X|^3). \] Equating both sides and canceling \(u(x)\): \[ -\,u'(x)\pi + \tfrac12 u''(x)\pi^2 + O(\pi^3) = \tfrac12 u''(x)\sigma^2 t^2 + O(t^3). \] Since the leading term on the right is order \(t^2\), we must have \(\pi(t)=O(t^2)\); hence \(\pi^2=O(t^4)\) and the quadratic/cubic terms in \(\pi\) are \(o(t^2)\). Therefore \[ -\,u'(x)\,\pi(t) \;=\; \tfrac12 u''(x)\sigma^2 t^2 + o(t^2), \] so \[ \pi(t) \;=\; \tfrac12\left(-\frac{u''(x)}{u'(x)}\right)\sigma^2 t^2 + o(t^2) = \tfrac12\,r(x)\,\sigma^2 t^2 + o(t^2). \] Affine invariance follows immediately: if \(\tilde u = a u + b\) with \(a&gt;0\), then \(\tilde u' = a u'\), \(\tilde u'' = a u''\), so \(-\tilde u''/\tilde u' = -u''/u'\). ∎ </div> <h3 id="interpretation-and-conclusion">Interpretation and Conclusion</h3> <p>The index $r(x)$ is not geometry for its own sake but a way of formalizing how fast marginal utility declines at wealth $x$. It measures the willingness of an individual to pay in order to eliminate small risks. In insurance theory, this is the excess above actuarially fair value; in finance, it is the foundation of equilibrium risk premia. My own interest was rekindled when I revisited CRRA preferences in the microfoundations of Lucas’s exchange economy and islands papers. CRRA utility is not just a convenient functional form: through the Arrow–Pratt formula it imposes a very particular scaling of risk aversion with wealth. The entire machinery of representative-agent macroeconomics inherits that assumption, often without much reflection.</p> <p>It is also worth stressing what lies beneath the definition of the risk premium. The construction presumes that the agent must compare the gamble with the certain payoff, with no option to walk away from both. This is the axiom of completeness at work, and it is precisely what guarantees that $\pi$ is well-defined. In real life, agents may refuse both contracts, but in the model world they cannot. The Arrow–Pratt index, so central to our theory of risk, therefore rests on both the calculus of concavity and the discipline of completeness. That hidden assumption is as much a part of the story as the derivative ratio itself.</p> <p>Pratt’s formula is elegant, but it belongs firmly to the domain of measurable risk. As Frank Knight reminded us a century ago, “uncertainty must be taken in a sense radically distinct from the familiar notion of risk.” The Arrow–Pratt index tells us how agents behave under small, quantifiable gambles; what it cannot capture is the deeper uncertainty that lies beyond variance, where probabilities themselves are ill-defined.</p> <hr/> <h2 class="bibliography">2018</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="chabiyo2018crash" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Crash Sensitivity and the Cross-Section of Expected Stock Returns</div> <div class="author"> Fousseni Chabi-Yo,&nbsp;Stefan Ruenzi,&nbsp;and&nbsp;Florian Weigert </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>Journal of Financial and Quantitative Analysis</em>, 2018 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> <h2 class="bibliography">1965</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="fama1965behavior" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">The behavior of stock-market prices</div> <div class="author"> Eugene F. Fama </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>The Journal of Business</em>, 1965 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> <h2 class="bibliography">1963</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="mandelbrot1963variation" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">The variation of certain speculative prices</div> <div class="author"> Benoit B. Mandelbrot </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>The Journal of Business</em>, 1963 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> <h2 class="bibliography">1959</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="sklar1959" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Fonctions de Répartition à n Dimensions et Leurs Marges</div> <div class="author"> Abe Sklar </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>Publ. Inst. Stat. Univ. Paris</em>, 1959 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional"/><category term="teaching"/><category term="project"/><category term="utility"/><category term="risk-aversion"/><category term="Arrow-Pratt"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A quick note on how the risk premium connects to derivatives of utility.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Copulas - the art of avoiding marginal distributions!</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/Copulas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Copulas - the art of avoiding marginal distributions!"/><published>2025-05-26T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-26T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/Copulas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/Copulas/"><![CDATA[<p>The simplest decision problem is forecasting the value of one variable in terms of another. We will focus on the relationship between stock prices and index prices, usually called a market model, in this blogpost. Our job as academics is to tease out the precise meaning of the word ‘relation’.</p> <p>Consider an imaginary table of stock price vs index price:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Stock Price (X)</th> <th>Index Price (Y)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>2</td> <td>45</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2</td> <td>52</td> </tr> <tr> <td>2</td> <td>48</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3</td> <td>52</td> </tr> <tr> <td>3</td> <td>60</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4</td> <td>65</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4</td> <td>68</td> </tr> <tr> <td>4</td> <td>70</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5</td> <td>68</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5</td> <td>75</td> </tr> <tr> <td>5</td> <td>80</td> </tr> <tr> <td>6</td> <td>80</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <blockquote> <p>How do we find a relation between the two variables?</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="from-functional-relations-to-distributions">From Functional Relations to Distributions</h3> <p>The figure below illustrates three types of relationships we can observe:</p> <ol> <li>Ideally, we would love to get a functional relation $Y=h(X)$, i.e. a unique value of $Y$ for each value of $X$. The economists favorite tool ‘linear regression’ is popular because who doesn’t love functional relations. Linear is easy so it sweetens the pot!</li> <li>However, in practice, when we collect data and stare at the table, we usually get multivalued function, i.e. $h(X)$ can be a set of values.</li> <li>When sufficient number of data collection experiments are repeated, the data usually has more information: we can keep track of the multiplicity of values. So we get a ‘distribution’!</li> </ol> <figure style="text-align: center;"> <img src="/assets/img/fun2dist.png" alt="Description" style="width: 70%; height: auto;"/> <figcaption style="margin-top: 0.5em; font-size: 0.9em; color: #666;"> <em>Figure: Three forms of relations.</em> </figcaption> </figure> <p>In summary, we may view a conditional distribution $\Pr\{Y=y \mid X=x\}$ as a ‘statistical function’. For every input value of $x$, it gives us a distribution of $y$ values instead of a single value. Traditionally, in probability theory, conditional distributions are computed using joint distributions of $(X,Y)$. Information about the marginal distributions is stored within the joint distribution.</p> <h3 id="copulas-capturing-dependence-without-marginals">Copulas: Capturing Dependence Without Marginals</h3> <p>The aim of this blogpost is to motivate an interesting form of ‘joint distribution’, called ‘Copula’, that forgets the marginal distribution information! Think of it as analogous to a linear relation after converting both the variables to percentages. So its like a relation between normalized variables.</p> <p>This becomes especially useful when there is no consensus on the marginal distributions of the variables involved. A good example is the distribution of daily stock returns. These are often assumed to follow a normal distribution, but in reality, large deviations (extreme returns) occur far too frequently for that assumption to hold. Recognizing this, Mandelbrot (in @mandelbrot1963variation) and Fama (in @fama1965behavior) later proposed using Lévy-stable distributions as more appropriate alternatives.</p> <blockquote> <p>If distribution of returns is controversial, can we study market models independent of such assumptions?</p> </blockquote> <p>YES! We can use <em>copulas</em>.</p> <p>The idea of copula is motivated by a cute mathematical observation.</p> <div class="math-block"> <strong>Proposition.</strong> Let \( X \) be a random variable with a continuous CDF \( F \) and let \( Y = F(X). \) Then \(Y\) is uniformly distributed on the interval \([0,1].\) </div> <div class="math-block proof"> <strong>Proof.</strong> Since \( F \) is continuous and increasing, it is invertible. By properties of cdf, we know that \(0 &lt; Y &lt; 1.\) Consider a real number \(y\) such that \(0 &lt; y &lt; 1\), let us compute the cdf of \(Y: \) $$ \begin{align} F_Y(y) &amp;= \Pr\{Y \leq y\} \\ &amp;= \Pr\{F(X) \leq y\} \\ &amp;= \Pr\{X \leq F^{-1}(y)\} \\ &amp;= F(F^{-1}(y)) \\ &amp;= y \end{align} $$ Hence, \( Y \sim \text{Uniform}(0,1) \). ∎ </div> <p>So we have a universal method to transform a random variable with known distribution into a uniform random variable! Now suppose we have two variables $X,Y$ with marginal cdfs $F_X,F_Y$, the joint cdf of the uniform random variables $U_X = F_X(X), U_Y=F_Y(Y)$ is called the <em>copula</em> of $X,Y$ (see @sklar1959).</p> <div class="math-block"> <strong>Definition.</strong> Let $X,Y$ be two random variables with marginal cdfs $F_X,F_Y$. Then the copula $C(u,v)$ is defined as \[ C(u,v) = \Pr\left\{X \leq F_X^{-1}(u),Y \leq F_Y^{-1}(v)\right\},\] for $0 &lt; u,v &lt; 1$. </div> <p>The copula has the following cool features:</p> <ol> <li>The copula is a joint distribution of two uniform random variables. The marginal distribution of $X,Y$ is lost and cannot be recovered from the copula.</li> <li>If $X,Y$ are independent, then copula $C(u,v) = uv$. If they are completely dependent, say $X=Y$, then $C(u,v) = \text{min}\{u,v\}$. Thus copula still tracks the relation between variables even though the marginal information is lost.</li> <li>Sklar’s theorem allows you to build a joint cdf by assembling a copula and a pair of marginal distributions!</li> </ol> <p>In finance, the controversial question of whether daily returns of stock prices are normally distributed can be side stepped with copulas. We can focus on a copula based market model where we estimate the copula of stock return and index return. The conditional distribution of stock crash given that the market has crashed is called the ‘market crash risk’. <a href="https://www.mse.ac.in/faculty/ekta/">Dr. Selarka</a>, my MA student Amritha, and I estimated the market crash risk for Nifty50 and it forms the main part of Amritha’s dissertation. Amritha has written python modules for copula estimation following the ideas in Chabi-Yo <em>et. al.</em> and I leave you with pretty pictures from her dissertation. If you are curious, read it and let us know your comments.</p> <figure style="text-align: center;"> <img src="/assets/img/copulas-amritha.png" alt="Description" style="width: 50%; height: auto;"/> <figcaption style="margin-top: 0.5em; font-size: 0.9em; color: #666;"> <em>Figure: If you are curious about these pretty pictures, read Amritha's dissertation. </em> </figcaption> </figure> <h2 class="bibliography">2018</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="chabiyo2018crash" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Crash Sensitivity and the Cross-Section of Expected Stock Returns</div> <div class="author"> Fousseni Chabi-Yo,&nbsp;Stefan Ruenzi,&nbsp;and&nbsp;Florian Weigert </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>Journal of Financial and Quantitative Analysis</em>, 2018 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> <h2 class="bibliography">1965</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="fama1965behavior" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">The behavior of stock-market prices</div> <div class="author"> Eugene F. Fama </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>The Journal of Business</em>, 1965 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> <h2 class="bibliography">1963</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="mandelbrot1963variation" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">The variation of certain speculative prices</div> <div class="author"> Benoit B. Mandelbrot </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>The Journal of Business</em>, 1963 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> <h2 class="bibliography">1959</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> </div> <div id="sklar1959" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Fonctions de Répartition à n Dimensions et Leurs Marges</div> <div class="author"> Abe Sklar </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>Publ. Inst. Stat. Univ. Paris</em>, 1959 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="professional"/><category term="teaching"/><category term="project"/><category term="probability"/><category term="stocks"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Market crash risk without marginal information?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Andre’s Reflection Trick</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Andres-reflection-trick/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Andre’s Reflection Trick"/><published>2024-09-29T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Andres-reflection-trick</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Andres-reflection-trick/"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s an interesting problem related to voting and ballot counts:</p> <p><strong>Suppose A and B win p and q votes respectively in an election with p &gt; q. While counting the ballots, what is the probability that A always remains ahead of B throughout the count?</strong></p> <p>The problem is recast graphically and then Andre’s beautiful insight solves the problem quickly. Watch it explained in this video:</p> <iframe style="display: block; margin: auto;" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ebKPaj9Pj6s?si=2NHw--F9A2G60vwM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cool"/><category term="math"/><category term="Voting"/><category term="problems"/><category term="Probability"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Probability problem on vote count.]]></summary></entry></feed>