<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-07T11:52:07+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Mathematic </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Combinatorics Problems</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Combinatorics-Problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combinatorics Problems"/><published>2024-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Combinatorics-Problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Combinatorics-Problems/"><![CDATA[<p>A 6 x 6 square is dissected into nine rectangles by lines parallel to its side such that all these rectangles have integer sides. Prove that there are always two congruent rectangles. <em>Proof:</em> We proceed by contradiction. If the square can be dissected into nine non-congruent rectangles, then we will show that the total area will exceed 36.</p> <p>We will enumerate the areas of the rectangles of sidelengths at most 6 units, along with the number of such non-congruent rectangles.</p> <p>| Area | a x b | number | | —- | ———— | —— | | 1 | 1 x 1 | 1 | | 2 | 1 x 2 | 1 | | 3 | 1 x 3 | 1 | | 4 | 1 x 4, 2 x 2 | 2 | | 5 | 1 x 5 | 1 | | 6 | 1x 6, 2 x 3 | 2 | | 8 | 2 x 4 | 1 | Total sum of 9 rectangles $\geq$ 1 + 2+ 3+4 +4 + 5 +6 +6 +8 = 39 This means that any dissection of a 6 x 6 square into 9 incongruent rectangles has atleast 39 sq units as area. But 6x6 square has area 36. So this is the required contradiction. <em>__</em></p> <p>The numbers 1, 2, 3, . . . , n are arranged in a particular order. One can swap any two adjacent numbers. Prove that after performing an odd number of such operations, the arrangement of the numbers thus obtained will differ from the original one. <em>Proof:</em></p> <hr/> <p>A teacher wrote the quadratic $x^2 +10x+20$ on the board. Then, each student either increased by $1$ or decreased by $1$ either the constant or the linear coefficient. Finally $x^2 +20x+10$ appeared. Did a quadratic expression with integer zeros necessarily appear on the board in the process? <em>Proof:</em> (sketch) Represent the polynomial $x^2+ax+b$ on the plane by the point $(a,b)$. students moves will create a path out of lattice points. Now the family of polynomials $x^2 + (n+1)x + n$ is represented by the set of lattice points on the line y=x-1. Since the starting and ending points lie on the either side, the path must cross the polynomial $x^2 + (n+1)x + n$ which has integer roots.</p> <hr/> <p>(BMO R2 2016) Naomi and Tom play a game, with Naomi going first. They take it in turns to pick an integer from 1 to 100, each time selecting an integer which no-one has chosen before. A player loses the game if, after their turn, the sum of all the integers chosen since the start of the game (by both of them) cannot be written as the difference of two square numbers. Determine if one of the players has a winning strategy, and if so, which.</p> <p><em>Proof:</em> I claim Naomi has a winning strategy. First we note that n cannot be written as difference of two squares iff $n \equiv 2 \mod 4$ . 25 numbers are 0,1,2,3 mod 4 from 1 to 100. Naomi’s strategy is</p> <ul> <li>Start with a 4</li> <li>If tom picks 1 mod 4, then choose a 3 mod 4 number and vice versa.</li> <li>If tom picks a multiple of 4, then write a multiple of 4.</li> <li>If tom picks 2 mod 4, rejoice. Naomi can always run her strategy because of the following reasons:</li> <li>Since there are odd number of multiples of 4, she will always be the last one to write a multiple of 4.</li> <li>Since there are equal numbers of 1 and 3 mod 4 numbers and she never starts with one of them, she will be the last one to write 1 or 3. Since she never has to write a 2 mod 4, she wins. —- (BMO R1 2017) Matthew has a deck of 300 cards numbered 1 to 300. He takes cards out of the deck one at a time and places the selected cards in a row, with each new card added at the right end of the row. Matthew must arrange for the mean of the numbers on the cards in the row to be an integer. If, at some point, there is no card remaining in the deck, which allows Matthew to continue, then he stops. When Matthew stopped, what was the smallest possible number of cards that he could have placed in the row? Give an example of such a row.</li> </ul> <p><em>Proof:</em> We claim the smallest possible number of cards is 17. First we show that Matthew must have placed at least 17 cards on the table. Suppose Matt has $k$ cards on the table and let us denote it by $x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_k$. If Matt can place a new card $x_{k+1}$ on the table, then we need (k+1) must divide $\sum_{i=1}^{k+1} x_i$ and thus \(x_{k+1}\equiv -(x_1+x_2+\ldots x_{k}) \mod (k+1).\)Let $a$ denote the congruence class of $-(x_1+x_2+\ldots x_{k})$ modulo $(k+1)$. The only way he cannot place card $x_{k+1}$ is if all the cards with $-a \mod (k+1)$ has already been placed on the table. Since each congruence class appears at most $\left\lfloor \dfrac{300}{k+1} \right\rfloor$ times. Since we have placed only $k$ cards, we must have \(\left\lfloor \dfrac{300}{k+1} \right\rfloor &lt; k+1\) This inequality is satisfied iff $k \geq 17$.</p> <p>Now we show k=17 can be achieved. Matt writes all the numbers of the form 1 mod 18 in increasing order. So he writes 17 numbers this way. Now the sum of the cards on the table is \(\sum_{k=0}^{16} (18k+1) = 18*(16*17)/2+17 \equiv 0+(-1) \mod 18.\) Now Matt has exhausted all the numbers of the form 1 mod 18 and thus can’t continue. So 17 cards is achievable.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A 6 x 6 square is dissected into nine rectangles by lines parallel to its side such that all these rectangles have integer sides. Prove that there are always two congruent rectangles. Proof: We proceed by contradiction. If the square can be dissected into nine non-congruent rectangles, then we will show that the total area will exceed 36.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Number Theory Problems</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Number-theory-Problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Number Theory Problems"/><published>2024-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Number-theory-Problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Number-theory-Problems/"><![CDATA[<p>(BMO R1 2009) Find all integers $x,y,z$ such that $x^2 + y^2 + z^2 =2(yz+1)$ and $x+y+z=4018$. <em>Proof</em>: The first equation can be written as $x^2 + (y-z)^2=2.$ So $x = \pm 1, (y-z)=\pm 1.$</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>x,(y-z)</th> <th>1</th> <th>-1</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>1</td> <td>$y+z=4017,y-z=1$</td> <td>$y+z=4017,y-z=-1$</td> </tr> <tr> <td>-1</td> <td>$y+z=4019,y-z=1$</td> <td>$y+z=4019,y-z=-1$</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Solving the four equations (by adding and subtracting), we get the solution set for (x,y,z) as ${(1,2009,2008),(-1,2010,2009),(-1,2009,2010),(1,2008,2009)}$.</p> <hr/> <p>(BMO R1 2011) Find all integers $n$ for which $n^2 +20n+11$ is a perfect square. <em>Proof</em>: We claim that $n=35,-55$ are the only solutions. We proceed by completing the square. We have to solve for n in the following equation: \((n+10)^2-89=k^2\) Now $(n+10)^2 - k^2 =89$ and thus $(n+10-k)(n+10+k)=89$ . Since 89 is prime, we get a couple of cases. <strong>Case 1:</strong> ${n+10-k,n+10+k}={1,89}$. Adding and simplifying, we get $n=35$. <strong>Case 2:</strong> ${n+10-k,n+10+k}={-1,-89}$. Adding and simplifying, we get $n=-55$.</p> <p><em>Aliter</em>: Let $N = n^2 + 20n + 11$. We note that for $n&gt; 35$, since $0 &lt; 2n-70$, by adding $n^2 + 18n + 81$ to both sides we see that $(n+9)^2 &lt; n^2 +20n + 11$. On the other hand, $n^2 + 20n + 11 &lt; n^2 + 20 n + 100$. Thus we have for $n &gt; 35$, \((n+9)^2 &lt; n^2 + 20n + 11 &lt; (n+10)^2.\) Since $N$ is bounded between two consecutive squares, it cannot be a perfect square. Since 11 is not a quadratic residue of 3 or 4, $N = k^2$ has no solutions if 3 or 4 divide $n$. Thus we have to check only 1,2,5,7,10,11,13,14,17,19,22,23,25,26,29,31,34,35. (Don’t do this in RMO) <del>It turns out 35 is the only solutions in this case.</del></p> <hr/> <p>(RMO 2002) Find all integers a, b, c, d satisfying the following relations: 1. $1\leq a\leq b\leq c\leq d$ 2. $ab+cd=a+b+c+d+3.$ <em>Proof</em>: Writing the second equation as \((a-1)(b-1)+(c-1)(d-1)=5.\) From the first relation, we see that $0 \leq (a-1)(b-1) \leq (c-1)(d-1)$. Thus we have three cases according to the partition of 5 as $0+5,1+4,2+3$: <strong>Case 1:</strong> $(a-1)(b-1)=0, (c-1)(d-1)=5.$ The first relation forces $a=1$, and $c=2,d=6$, $b=1$ or $2$. So the possible solutions in this case are $(1,1,2,6),(1,2,2,6).$ <strong>Case 2:</strong> $(a-1)(b-1)=1, (c-1)(d-1)=4.$ The second equation can be factored in two ways 2 x 2 and 1 x 4. The first relation forces $a=2,b=2$, and $c=2,d=5$ or $c=d=3$. So the possible solutions in this case are $(2,2,2,5),(2,2,3,3).$ <strong>Case 3:</strong> $(a-1)(b-1)=2, (c-1)(d-1)=3.$ <del>No solution because relation 1 fails.</del></p> <hr/> <p>(RMO 2013) Prove that there do not exist natural numbers $x$ and $y$ , with $x&gt;1$ , such that \(\dfrac{x^7 −1}{x-1} = y^5 +1.\) <em>Proof:</em> Rearranging we get \(\dfrac{x^7-x}{x-1}=y^5.\) Simplifying the expression we get \(x(x^2+x+1)(x^3+1)=y^5.\)</p> \[\begin{eqnarray} (x^2+x+1,x^3+1) &amp;= (x^2+x+1,x^3+1-x(x^2+x+1))\\ &amp;= (x^2+x+1,1-x^2-x)\\ &amp;= (x^2+x+1,2) \in \{1,2\} \end{eqnarray}\] <p>We see that if x is even, then both $x^2+x+1,x^3+1$ are odd. If x is odd, then exactly one of them is even. At any rate, both are not even and thus $(x^2+x+1,x^3+1) = 1$. Clearly, $(x,x^2+x+1)=1, (x,x^3+1)=1$. Thus a product of three numbers, that are pairwise coprime, is a fifth power. <strong>Fact:</strong> If a perfect $n$th power can be factored into pairwise coprime numbers, then the factors themselves are perfect $n$th powers. From the fact and our claims above we see that $x,x^2+x+1,x^3+1$ are perfect fifth powers. So $x=z^5, x^2+x+1=u^5, x^3+1=v^5$ and thus $(z^3)^5 + 1 = v^5$ . Now $x&gt; 1$, and thus we have $z^3&gt; 1,$ so no there is no solution since there are no consecutive fifth powers of natural numbers.</p> <p>For $n &gt; 1$, the the only integer solutions of $a^n = b^n +1$ is $b=0,a=1$ and when n is odd $b=-1,a=0$ .<br/> <em>Proof:</em> We prove the claim by case analysis: <strong>Case 1:</strong> First we assume a,b are non-negative integers. Note that $a&gt;b$ . Since $a-b$ divides $a^n - b^n$, we conclude $a-b=1$. Plugging in $a=b+1$, we get \(\sum_{k=1}^{n-1}\binom{n}{k}b^k = 0.\) Thus $b=0,a=1.$<br/> <strong>Case 2:</strong> Now if $a,b$ are non-positive, then set $a=-u, b=-v$ so that $u,v$ are non-negative. Now if n is odd we see that \(-u^n = -v^n + 1 \implies v^n = u^n+1.\) So we are in Case 1 and thus $u=0$ and $v=1$. Therefore $a=0, b=-1$.</p> <hr/> <p>(BMO R1 2015) A positive integer is called <em>charming</em> if it is equal to 2 or is of the form $3^i 5^j$ where i and j are non-negative integers. Prove that every positive integer can be written as a sum of different charming integers.</p> <p>We need the following lemma <strong>Lemma:</strong> For any positive integer $n &gt; 2$ there exists $i,j &gt; 0$ such that \(3^i 5^j \leq n &lt; 2 (3^i 5^j).\)<em>Proof:</em> We proceed by contradiction. Suppose the given statement is false, i.e. There exists positive integer n &gt; 2, for all $i,j &gt;0$ such that $2(3^i5^j) \leq n$ or $n &lt; 3^i5^j$. Choose $i_0,j_0$ such that $3^{i_0}5^{j_0} &lt; n$ and is the largest such. For our $i_0,j_0$, we have $2(3^{i_0}5^{j_0}) \leq n.$</p> <p>This means there is an positive integer $n&gt;2$ such that $2 (3^{i_0} 5^{j_0}) \leq n &lt; 3^{i_0+1}5^{j_0},$ for any $i,j$. If $j&gt;0$, then we claim \(3^{i+2}5^{j-1} &lt; n &lt; 2(3^{i+2}5^{j-1})\) $3^{i+2}5^{j-1} &lt; 2(3^i5^j)\leq n &lt; 3^{i+1}5^j &lt; 2(3^{i+2}5^{j-1}).$ So $i &gt; 0$, <del>a similar proof can be given.</del> $\blacksquare$</p> <p><em>Proof:</em> We proceed by strong induction. Let P(n) denote the proposition: “The number n can be written as a sum of different charming integers.” <strong>Base case:</strong> P(1) is true since $1= 3^0$. <strong>Strong induction hypothesis:</strong> $P(n)$ is true for all $n &lt; k$. <strong>Strong induction claim:</strong> $P(k)$ is true. <em>Proof:</em> First we note that $P(2)$ is true since 2 is given to be charming. For k&gt; 2, the lemma states that there exists $i,j &gt; 0$ such that \(3^i 5^j \leq k &lt; 2 (3^i 5^j).\) Let $m = k - 3^i5^j$ and thus $0 \leq m &lt; 3^i5^j$. Since $m &lt; 3^i 5^j \leq k$, we have $m &lt; k.$ If $m=0$, then $k=3^i5^j$ and thus k is charming. So $P(k)$ is true. On the other hand if $k &gt; m &gt; 0$, from strong induction claim, we have m is a sum of different charming numbers. Since $m &lt; 3^i5^j$, the number $3^i5^j$ cannot appear in any decomposition of m into different charming numbers. Therefore if we replace $m$ by sum of any set of charming numbers \(k = m + 3^i5^j\) then k is a sum of different charming numbers.</p> <p>240 = c + (240-c). If we choose largest possible c, then perhaps c &gt; 240 -c =&gt; 2c &gt; 240 &gt; c &lt;=&gt; c&lt; 240 &lt; 2c</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(BMO R1 2009) Find all integers $x,y,z$ such that $x^2 + y^2 + z^2 =2(yz+1)$ and $x+y+z=4018$. Proof: The first equation can be written as $x^2 + (y-z)^2=2.$ So $x = \pm 1, (y-z)=\pm 1.$]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Survey of the stable marriage problem</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Stable-Marriage-Survey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Survey of the stable marriage problem"/><published>2024-09-30T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Stable-Marriage-Survey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Stable-Marriage-Survey/"><![CDATA[<p>In 2012, the Nobel Prize in Economic Sciences was awarded to Alvin Roth and Lloyd Shapley for their work on designing practical market systems. At the heart of this recognition was a deceptively simple mathematical problem known as the Stable Marriage Problem, which has become a key player in matching processes that shape our daily lives—from job placements to college admissions and organ transplants.</p> <p>The Stable Marriage Problem was first introduced in a 1962 paper by David Gale and Lloyd Shapley, who proposed a straightforward algorithm to solve the following theoretical conundrum: Suppose there are \(n\) men and \(n\) women who are eager to be married. Each participant has <em>strictly</em> ranked <em>all</em> the members of the opposite gender in the order of their preference. Suppose a matchmaker matches the men and women. Now, if a man and a woman find that they prefer each other over their partners, they have a great incentive to break their marriages and choose each other. Such a situation is undesirable because we expect marriages to be stable. So we wonder</p> <blockquote> <p>Can we always marry the men and women off so that no two people prefer each other over their matched partners?</p> </blockquote> <p>Note that “stable match” is a property of all the marriages and not a property of an individual couple. This is so because stability depends on the options outside the marriage.</p> <p>Let us begin with an example: Suppose Anthara (A), Bhavana (B), and Chaitra (C) will be matched with advith (a), balaji (b), and charan (c). We will denote their preference list :</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th>advith</th> <th>balaji</th> <th>charan</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Anthara</td> <td>a,B</td> <td>c,A</td> <td>b,A</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Bhavana</td> <td>c,A</td> <td>a,B</td> <td>b,B</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Chaithra</td> <td>a,C</td> <td>b,C</td> <td>c,C</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>The preference list of women is read along the rows and for the men it is along the columns. For instance, Bhavana prefers charan over advith and advith over balaji. An example of a stable marriage would be the following pairing advith marries Bhavana, balaji marries Chaithra and charan marries Anthara. We will denote this stable match by {aB,bC,cA}.</p> <p><a href="https://www.eecs.harvard.edu/cs286r/courses/fall09/papers/galeshapley.pdf">Gale and Shapely</a> (1967) proved that a stable match exists no matter the preference lists of the participants. They even proposed an algorithm to find a stable match! In their algorithm, men propose to women in rounds. Women can only lock (temporarily accept) or reject men each round. A locked man can only propose once he is rejected. At any point, proposed women will have locked in one man. Let us take a quick look at their “deferred acceptance” algorithm:</p> <ul> <li>In the first round, the men propose to the highest-ranked women on their list. The women may receive multiple proposals or none at all. If they receive multiple proposals, each woman chooses the most preferred man available and tells him that she is considering his proposal (thereby locking him). She rejects the other men.</li> <li>In the next round, the rejected men propose to their next preferred woman. At this point, only if any woman gets a more preferred man will she reject the one she is considering. Now, she considers the more preferred man (thereby locks him).</li> <li>The rounds continue, with rejected men proposing to the most preferred among the remaining women and women locking/rejecting according to the previous bullet point. The algorithm terminates when men have no new women to propose to. Finally, women marry the men they are considering. By the end of the algorithm, every woman would be proposed, and thus, all participants could be paired off. Gale and Shapely proved that the marriage found by the described algorithm will always be stable.</li> </ul> <p>If there are multiple stable marriages, how does one compare them? In our example, M1={aB,bC,cA} and M2={aA,bC,cB} are stable matches. The stable marriage {aB,bC,cA} is better for men (called <em>men-optimal-stable-matching</em> or <em>MOSM</em>) since they get more preferred partners than {aA,bC,cB}. But for women, it is the opposite. Among two stable marriages $M_1, M_2$ we say \(M_1 \leq M_2\) if, for every man, the wife assigned in $M_2$ is not preferred less than the one in \(M_1\). Gale and Shapely showed that their algorithm will always find the marriage that is the best possible match for men (the proposers), which is also the worst possible for the women (the proposed) for the order \(\leq\).</p> <p>In a standard economics setup, the stability of prices is an indicator of the efficient allocation of resources to participants. But in markets like residency programs for doctors or college admissions for students, we are interested in efficient allocation across two different kinds of participants without prices! Economists can rejoice since the algorithm provides an efficient allocation (i.e. a stable match). Furthermore, computer scientists can rejoice since the algorithm terminates at a maximum of \(n^2-2n+2\) rounds. So, we have a polynomial time algorithm (meaning fast algorithm) to find the marriages.</p> <p>Conway discovered that the collection of all stable marriages, with the order \(\leq\) discussed above, forms a beautiful mathematical object called a “distributive lattice”. This is discussed in Knuth’s lucid exposition. Irving and Leather used the distributive lattice structure to show that listing all possible, <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/10.1137/0215048">stable marriages is a hard computer science problem</a>. Blair proved a converse to Conway’s observation. He revealed that every finite distributive lattice is a set of stable marriages.</p> <p>Knuth added a stochastic angle to the problem by assuming that preference lists are chosen randomly and n is large (asymptotic analysis). In the described algorithm, if a man has made $k$ proposals by the end, he will marry the woman ranked \(k\) in his list. So, the average number of proposals is also the average wife rank. Knuth/Prescott showed that the average number of proposals is roughly \(n \ln n\) and thus, the average wife’s rank is roughly \(\ln n\) . The same analysis shows the average husband’s rank is \(\frac{n}{\ln n}\). Note that if you put \(n=3000\), then the average wife rank is 8 and average husband rank is 375. Low husband rank is not surprising considering that Gale-Shapely algorithm always finds the worst matches for women, even on average we expect it to be bad.</p> <p>Interestingly, in 2017, Ashlagi <em>et al</em> showed that if the matching problem was between n+1 men and n women, the average husband rank is $\ln n$ and the average wife rank is \(\frac{n}{\ln n}\) (i.e. the rank situation flips!). This shows that there is extreme competition in matching markets. If men propose then we denote the situation by man-optimal-stable-matching (MOSM) and if women propose we denote the situation by WOSM. In a setting with 40 women, and n men, the figure shows the average wife rank has a sharp jump when the number of men cross 40 irrespective of who is doing the proposing. So the shorter side of the market gets one of their top choices with very high probability.</p> <p><img src="/downloads/MWOSM.gif" alt="Competition in unbalanced markets"/></p> <p>The fact that proposed (women) gets a least preferred match among all stable marriages is good motivation for them to lie about their preferences. So the natural question is whether women can gain a better outcome by lying about their preferences. The answer is <a href="http://www.eecs.harvard.edu/cs286r/courses/fall09/papers/roth.pdf">yes!</a> . In our example, if Anthara decides to lie about her preferences and announces that she prefers a&gt;b&gt;c (instead of her real preference a&gt;c&gt;b), then the Gale-Shapely algorithm will produce the match M2 which is women-optimal. On the other hand, Roth shows that in any procedure which produces optimal results for one side, truthful revelation of preferences is a dominant strategy (for men in Gale-Shapely algorithm for instance). The incentive to misrepresent preferences motivates the model of a non-cooperative game where the strategy set of participants is the collection of possible preference lists they might state. Roth proved that if the agents misstate their preferences optimally with respect to each other, i.e. their (mis)stated preferences form a Nash equilibrium, then an algorithm like Gale-Shapely’s will yield stable outcomes in terms of their agents true preferences. If the Gale-Shapely algorithm is used, Roth showed that men have no incentive to lie.</p> <p>The structural simplicity of the stable marriage problem belies its immense practical utility. Variants like the residency matching market, organ donor markets, high school admissions market are studied seriously today. Roth seriously studied the problem motivated by the residency matching problem. The National Residency Matching Program (NRMP) in the U.S. was forced to change tactics because the algorithm could be manipulated by the proposed through misstating their preferences. In 1984 they changed their system to applicant proposing from hospital proposing. The existence of stable solutions, speed of the matching algorithm, the potential for games and the competitiveness of the stable matching market continues to enthral mathematicians, economists, and computer scientists.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Survey"/><category term="StableMarriage"/><category term="gametheory"/><category term="economics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An article for Nidhi]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stable marriage problem?</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/less-technical-Stable-Marriage-Survey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stable marriage problem?"/><published>2024-09-30T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/less-technical-Stable-Marriage-Survey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/less-technical-Stable-Marriage-Survey/"><![CDATA[<p>In 2012, Alvin Roth and Lloyd Shapley were awarded the Nobel Prize in Economic Sciences for their groundbreaking work on practical market systems. The heart of their achievement lay in solving a deceptively simple mathematical puzzle known as the <strong>Stable Marriage Problem</strong>. Though initially theoretical, this problem has since revolutionised how we handle real-world matching processes that impact everyday life—everything from job placements to college admissions and organ transplants.</p> <p>The <strong>Stable Marriage Problem</strong> was introduced in 1962 by David Gale and Lloyd Shapley. Their goal? To solve a tricky question: how do you match two sets of individuals (say, men and women) so that no one would prefer someone else over their current partner? In other words, how do you create a “stable” arrangement where no two people would leave their current matches for each other? This might seem abstract, but the consequences of match instability can be serious—think about hospitals competing for medical residents or students competing for university spots.</p> <h3 id="the-problem-and-solution-a-simple-algorithm"><strong>The Problem and Solution: A Simple Algorithm</strong></h3> <p>Gale and Shapley framed the problem like this: Imagine there are <strong>n</strong> men and <strong>n</strong> women, each of whom ranks everyone on the opposite side in order of preference. The matchmaker’s task is to marry them off so that no pair of individuals would prefer each other over their assigned spouses, thus ensuring a “stable” marriage.</p> <p>To see how this works, let’s imagine three women: Anthara (A), Bhavana (B), and Chaithra (C), who will be matched with three men: Advith (a), Balaji (b), and Charan (c). Each person has a preference list, like this:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th>advith</th> <th>balaji</th> <th>charan</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Anthara</td> <td>a,B</td> <td>c,A</td> <td>b,A</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Bhavana</td> <td>c,A</td> <td>a,B</td> <td>b,B</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Chaithra</td> <td>a,C</td> <td>b,C</td> <td>c,C</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>In this scenario, Anthara prefers advith over charan and charan over balaji, and similarly, balaji prefers Anthara over Bhavana and Bhavana over Chaithra, etc. Gale and Shapley’s algorithm works by having the men propose to women in rounds. If a woman receives multiple proposals, she “locks in” the one she prefers and rejects the others. The rejected men then propose to the next woman on their list, and the process continues until everyone is paired up. The result? A stable set of marriages where no one has an incentive to swap partners.</p> <h3 id="a-guaranteed-stable-matchbut-who-wins"><strong>A Guaranteed Stable Match—But Who Wins?</strong></h3> <p>The beauty of Gale and Shapley’s algorithm is that it guarantees a stable match exists for any set of preferences. But who benefits more, men or women? It turns out that the side doing the proposing (in this case, the men) ends up better off, leading to a <strong>men-optimal stable matching (MOSM)</strong>. This means the men end up with their most preferred possible partners within the set of stable matches, while the women get the least preferred option among the stable possibilities.</p> <p>This result has fascinating real-world implications. Fairness and efficiency are critical in markets like residency programs, college admissions, and even organ donation. Gale and Shapley’s work showed that, without needing prices or money, we could still achieve stable, fair matches between two groups—whether students and universities or doctors and hospitals. Roth’s <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/195998">article</a> explains the origins and history of the residency match programs, which show that the concerns of the participants were about fairness and efficiency.</p> <h3 id="competition-and-market-dynamics"><strong>Competition and Market Dynamics</strong></h3> <p>The competition for top choices makes matching markets like these even more interesting. Imagine a situation where there are <strong>n+1 men</strong> and <strong>n women</strong>. Now, the competition on the men’s side intensifies because one man won’t get matched. Studies by researchers like Ashlagi and others in 2017 showed that when there’s an imbalance in the numbers—more men than women, for instance—the men’s average outcomes worsen, while the women’s outcomes improve dramatically.</p> <p>In the balanced case (equal numbers of men and women), the proposing side (men in this case) tend to do better, securing higher-ranked partners. But the tables turn when you have an extra man in the market. The women are matched with their higher preferences, while the average “rank” of the man’s wife significantly drops. The reverse happens when the women outnumber the men.</p> <p>This reflects an essential aspect of competition in matching markets: the smaller side (with fewer participants) often gains a competitive edge, getting more of their top choices. So, <strong>which side of the market is “smaller” becomes a crucial factor in determining who will have better outcomes</strong>.</p> <h3 id="complexity-and-efficiency"><strong>Complexity and Efficiency</strong></h3> <p>On the surface, the problem seems simple, but the efficiency of the solution is what makes it so powerful. The algorithm runs in <strong>polynomial time</strong>, meaning it can quickly handle large sets of participants. For example, matching 3,000 medical students with hospitals won’t take forever—just a few thousand steps. This makes the algorithm not just theoretical but highly practical for real-world applications. Forbes <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/prernasinha/2015/03/24/quantifying-harmony-the-matchmaking-algorithm-that-pairs-residents-with-hospitals-students-with-schools/">reported</a> that the algorithm took 17 seconds to match over 30,000 doctors to hospitals in 2015.</p> <h3 id="challenges-and-manipulations"><strong>Challenges and Manipulations</strong></h3> <p>One interesting aspect of the stable marriage problem is the potential for manipulation. If the proposing side (say, men) knows they can secure better outcomes by misrepresenting their preferences, will they do it? Roth, who extended Gale and Shapley’s work, explored this in the context of residency matching. He found that in some cases, one side can gain an advantage by lying about their preferences, leading to mismatches that benefit them but harm the system’s overall fairness.</p> <p>This issue was brought to attention in the U.S. when the National Residency Matching Program (NRMP) had a system where hospitals were initially the ones proposing to doctors. Over time, the NRMP had to adjust its process because doctors began manipulating their preference lists. In 1984, the system switched to doctor-proposing, which reduced the opportunity for manipulation.</p> <h3 id="why-it-matters-today"><strong>Why It Matters Today</strong></h3> <p>The Stable Marriage Problem’s influence extends far beyond its origins in theoretical mathematics. Today, its principles are applied in the design of many matching markets:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Medical residency programs</strong>, where young doctors are paired with hospitals.</li> <li><strong>School choice programs</strong>, where students are matched with public schools based on their preferences and availability.</li> <li><strong>Organ donation systems</strong>, which need to match donors with recipients based on compatibility.</li> </ul> <p>Though the problem itself is structurally simple, the impact of its solution is profound. The dynamics of <strong>competition</strong> in matching markets, the <strong>efficiency</strong> of the algorithm, and the potential for <strong>manipulation</strong> continue to drive new research and applications in fields ranging from economics to computer science. As our world becomes more interconnected and our markets more complex, the principles behind stable matching will only grow in importance, ensuring fairness, stability, and efficiency in matching people to the opportunities they seek.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Survey"/><category term="StableMarriage"/><category term="gametheory"/><category term="economics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An article for Nidhi]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Andre’s Reflection Trick</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Andres-reflection-trick/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Andre’s Reflection Trick"/><published>2024-09-29T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Andres-reflection-trick</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Andres-reflection-trick/"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s an interesting problem related to voting and ballot counts:</p> <p><strong>Suppose A and B win p and q votes respectively in an election with p &gt; q. While counting the ballots, what is the probability that A always remains ahead of B throughout the count?</strong></p> <p>The problem is recast graphically and then Andre’s beautiful insight solves the problem quickly. Watch it explained in this video:</p> <iframe style="display: block; margin: auto;" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ebKPaj9Pj6s?si=2NHw--F9A2G60vwM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cool"/><category term="math"/><category term="Voting"/><category term="problems"/><category term="Probability"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Probability problem on vote count.]]></summary></entry></feed>