<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-30T11:42:09+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Mathematic </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Levy Stable processes in Quant Finance</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/Survey-of-Levy-stable-processes-in-Quantitative-Finance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Levy Stable processes in Quant Finance"/><published>2025-01-22T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/Survey-of-Levy-stable-processes%20in%20Quantitative-Finance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/Survey-of-Levy-stable-processes-in-Quantitative-Finance/"><![CDATA[<p>The use of stable laws in asset price distributions and the derivatives market is the subject matter of this survey. In particular, we are interested in estimating the risk and effect of liquidity in a market with assets satisfying a stable distribution.</p> <p><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2328817">This paper</a> explains, “This paper provides empirical support for the hypothesis that ARCH is a manifestation of the daily time dependence in the rate of information arrival to the market for individual stocks.” #information-stocks</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="stochastic-process,"/><category term="research"/><category term="stable-laws"/><category term="risk"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts, Outline and Comments]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Galois theory for a high school student.</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/A-high-school-application-of-Galois-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Galois theory for a high school student."/><published>2025-01-04T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-04T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/A%20high%20school%20application%20of%20Galois%20theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/A-high-school-application-of-Galois-theory/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>A polynomial in one variable $x$ with real coefficients is an expression that can be made by adding, multiplying, subtracting real numbers and the variable $x$. For instance, consider the expression $x^2 + 3x +2$, which is simply the wordy algorithm</p> <blockquote> <p>Think of a number, square it and add it to three times to the original number. Finally add two to it.</p> </blockquote> <p>We will call the expression $P(x)$. When the algorithm is carried out on a particular number $n$, we say that th polynomial is “evaluated” at $n$ and denote this operation by $eval_P(n)=P(n)$. So if $n=5$, then \[eval_P(5) = P(5) = 5^2 +3\cdot 5+ 2=42.\]</p> <p>As it is usual in mathematics, we start studying the collection of all polynomials as an interesting object. Usually this is done in high school.</p> <h1 id="high-school-polynomial-theory">High School Polynomial theory</h1> <p>In high school we learn the divisibility theory of polynomials. First we learn long division which teaches us to compute a quotient and remainder when two polynomials are divided.</p> <p>A monic polynomial is a polynomial whose leading coefficient is one. When a polynomial is evaluated at a number, if it vanishes it is called a <em>root</em> of the polynomial. <em>Example:</em> The polynomial $x^2 - 3x + 2$ vanishes iff $x=1$ or $x=2$. So we say the set ${1,2}$ is the set of roots of the polynomial $x^2 - 3x + 2$.</p> <p>Next we learn the factor theorem: A polynomial $Q(x)$ vanishes at $x=r$ iff $(x-r)$ divides $Q(x)$. This is really cool since we now have an alternative definition for a root. We can say r is a root of $Q(x)$ if $(x-r)$ is a factor of $Q(x)$. In fact this definition is superior since we can define more subtle properties of roots (i.e. multiplicity of roots, see below.)</p> <p>A converse question is naturally suggested: Can we recover the polynomial from the roots? The answer is yes if we are allowed to redefine the notion of roots.</p> <ul> <li>$(x-1)^2$ and $x-1$ both have the same ‘set’ of roots. So we cannot definitely recover the polynomial from simply <em>the set of roots</em>.</li> <li>We change the definition of <em>root</em>: We say a number $r$ is a root of a polynomial $Q(x)$ with <em>multiplicity k</em> for some natural $k$ if $(x-r)^k$ divides $Q(x)$ but $(x-r)^{k+1}$ does not divide $Q(x)$.</li> <li>A better structure for the root data is a ‘<em>divisor</em>’ (sorry for a confusing name, stupid math people!) which is defined as a sum $n_1[r_1]+n_2[r_2]+…+n_k[r_k]$ which indicates that root $r_i$ appears $n_i$ times. For instance $2[1]$ is the divisor of roots for $(x-1)^2$ whereas $[1]$ is divisor of roots for $(x-1)$.</li> </ul> <p><em>Example:</em> What is the collection of all quadratic polynomials that have $[1]+[2]$ as the divisor of roots? The answer is the set \[\{k(x-1)(x-2)| k \in \mathbb{R}\}\] and it can be proved using factor theorem. By setting $k=1$, we see that a monic polynomial $x^2-3x+2$ is uniquely determined by the divisor $[1]+[2]$.</p> <p><em>Example:</em> The root divisor of polynomial $x^4 - 6x^3 + 13x^2 - 12x + 4$ is $2[1]+2[2]$.</p> <p>A divisor is simply an expression of the type $n_1[r_1]+n_2[r_2]+…+n_k[r_k]$ where $n_i$ are natural numbers and $r_i$ are numbers. With the divisor of roots definition, and factor theorem we have a nice converse.</p> <blockquote> <p>(Exercise!) Given a divisor, there is a unique monic polynomial whose divisor of roots is the given divisor.</p> </blockquote> <p>Another question that might appear in your mind is whether every polynomial has a root? We have to be careful about the numbers we are dealing with but the answer is affirmative. The affirmative answer was one of the breakthroughs in 19th century mathematics. But to answer it, we have to invent complex numbers. Consider a polynomial $x^2 + 1=0$. If we label one of the roots as $i$, then the other root is $-i$ . Just acknowledging the existence of the symbol has a serious consequence: Now a polynomial $(x-a)^2 +b^2 =0$ has solutions $x=a\pm ib$. The numbers of the form $a+ib$ where $a,b \in \mathbb{R}$ are called complex numbers. Although they were invented to solve quadratic equations, the breakthrough result of 19th century states</p> <blockquote> <p>(Fundamental theorem of algebra) Every polynomial with real coefficients has a divisor of complex number roots.</p> </blockquote> <p>The summary is a gorgeous correspondence:</p> <blockquote> <p>The set of divisors (with complex numbers) is in one-one correspondence with the set of monic polynomials with real coefficients.</p> </blockquote> <p>We will call this “the basic correspondence”.</p> <h1 id="symmetry-of-the-roots">Symmetry of the roots</h1> <p>Very broadly, a symmetry is a transformation that leaves an object unchanged. The map that sends a complex number $a+ib$ to $a-ib$ is called <em>complex conjugation</em>. In case of polynomials with real coefficients, complex conjugation always leaves the divisor of roots unchanged (Exercise!), so its a symmetry!</p> <p><em>Example:</em> Clearly $[i]+[-i]$ corresponds to the polynomial $x^2+1$ (under the basic correspondence). Complex conjugation sends the divisor $[i]+[-i]$ to $[-i]+[i]$. We see that the divisor is unchanged in this example.</p> <p>The key reason for this behaviour is that complex conjugation respects addition, multiplication, division, subtraction and further, it leaves real numbers unchanged. Since a polynomial with real coefficients is built using these operations, we see that whenever $z$ is a root of a polynomial (with real coeffs), so is the complex conjugate of $z$. Another way to say this is: The set ${a+ib,a-ib}$ is either a root set of a poly with real coefficients or neither of them are roots. Its a “take it all or leave it all offer”.</p> <p>Sometimes a polynomial might be “more symmetric”. Let us explore the meaning of this with an example. Consider the polynomial $Q(x) = x^4 -10x^2 + 1$, we see that if $r$ is a root of $Q(x)$, then so is $-r$. Additionally, we see that $1/r$ is also a root (try evaluating it!). Finally this means that if $r$ is a root, so is $-1/r$. Even though we have not solved the polynomial, we know that a quadruple ${r,1/r,-r,-1/r}$ is either the set of roots or none of them are roots. Its again a “take it all or leave it all offer”, but now there are four elements. So it is “more symmetric”. Such sets of roots are called conjugates. We want to find transformations, analogous to complex conjugation, that send roots to other roots which preserve arithmetic operations.</p> <p>We continue with the example of $Q(x) = x^4 -10x^2 + 1$. Note that the roots of $Q(x)$ are real numbers (one can explicitly solve them since its a quadratic in $x^2$ and the roots are $\{\pm\sqrt{2}\pm\sqrt{3}\}$). Clearly if the transformations leave real numbers unchanged, we will have only identity transformation in this case. So we modify the problem:</p> <blockquote> <p>Motivated by complex conjugation, are there transformations that send one root of $Q(x)$ to another which preserve addition, multiplication, division, subtraction. It should leave rational numbers unchanged.</p> </blockquote> <p>If we want transformations that preserve all the arithmetic operations and rationals along with the ability to send roots to roots, we should create a domain of the transformation containing the roots, the rationals and the domain should be closed under the arithmetic operations. A set that is closed under the four arithmetic operations is called a “field” and if the field K contains another field L inside it, then we say $K/L$ is a field extension over $L$. The ‘smallest’ field that contains rationals and all the roots of a polynomial $P(x)$ is called the <em>splitting field of P(x)</em>.</p> <p><em>Example:</em> The collection of all the expressions formed by adding, multiplying, dividing and subtracting the roots is denoted by \[K:=\mathbb{Q}(r,1/r)=\{a+b\sqrt{2}+c\sqrt{3}+d\sqrt{6}|a,b,c,d \in \mathbb{Q}\}.\]</p> <ul> <li>$K$ contains all the roots of $Q(x)$ and is closed under all the arithmetic operations.</li> <li>$K/\mathbb{Q}$ is a field extension over $\mathbb{Q}$ and is the splitting field of $Q(x)$.</li> <li>Also note that $K$ is a vector space over $\mathbb{Q}$ and dimension of $K$ is $4$ (not obvious).</li> </ul> <p>It turns out that we have conjugation (invertible) transformations on $K$ \[\sigma_1(a+b\sqrt{2}+c\sqrt{3}+d\sqrt{6}) = a+b\sqrt{2}+c\sqrt{3}+d\sqrt{6}\] \[\sigma_2(a+b\sqrt{2}+c\sqrt{3}+d\sqrt{6}) = a-b\sqrt{2}+c\sqrt{3}-d\sqrt{6}\] \[\sigma_3(a+b\sqrt{2}+c\sqrt{3}+d\sqrt{6}) = a+b\sqrt{2}-c\sqrt{3}-d\sqrt{6}\] \[\sigma_4(a+b\sqrt{2}+c\sqrt{3}+d\sqrt{6}) = a-b\sqrt{2}-c\sqrt{3}+d\sqrt{6}\]</p> <p>So we found a way to create 4 symmetry transformations that send roots of $Q(x)$ to their conjugates. The novelty was in constructing a domain called “a field” which supports the symmetry transformations. An invertible map ( a transformation) from a field to another field that preserves the four basic arithmetic operations is called a <em>field isomorphism</em>. The collection of transformations of a field extension $K/L$ that preserves basic arithmetic operations (i.e. field isomorphisms from K to K) and the elements of $L$ is called the Galois group $Gal(K/L)$. Like complex conjugation, the elements of the Galois group permute the roots of a polynomial whose coefficients come from $L$.</p> <p>A group is a collection of transformations with the property that a composition of two transformation in the group is again an element of the group. The precise definition demands existence of identity and inverse transformations in the group.</p> <p><em>Example:</em> Consider the previous example and look at the set $\{\sigma_1,\sigma_2,\sigma_3,\sigma_4\}$ . First we note that $\sigma_1$ is the identity transformation. But you can verify that $\sigma_i \circ \sigma_i = \sigma_1$ for $i=1,2,3,4$. Next note that $\sigma_2 \circ \sigma_3 = \sigma_4$ . You can use these relations to show that any composition of two transformations is again an element of the form $\sigma_i$. So the set $\{\sigma_1,\sigma_2,\sigma_3,\sigma_4\}$ is a group. Note that $\{\sigma_1,\sigma_2,\sigma_3,\sigma_4\} \subseteq Gal(K/\mathbb{Q})$ since these transformations preserve basic operations and rational numbers.</p> <p>Now we see a curious relation: It looks like</p> <ul> <li>Every element of $K$, the splitting field of $Q(x)$, can be written as a linear combination of 4 elements.</li> <li>There are 4 transformations on $K$ that leave $\mathbb{Q}$ unchanged and preserve arithmetic operations. The number 4 appearing repeatedly is no coincidence. A couple of theorems of Galois theory tells us that it is always true. The precise statement can be stated using vector space language.</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>If $P(x)$ is a polynomial with rational coeffs and it has no non-trivial factors over rationals, then the splitting field of $P(x)$ is a vector space over $\mathbb{Q}$ with dimension equal to the degree of the polynomial.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Let $K/\mathbb{Q}$ be a splitting field of a polynomial $P(x)$, and suppose the dimension of the vector space $K$ is $d$. The number of elements in $Gal(K/\mathbb{Q})$ is d.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Example:</em> We have already argued that $\{\sigma_1,\sigma_2,\sigma_3,\sigma_4\} \subseteq Gal(K/\mathbb{Q})$. From the above theorem, we see that $\{\sigma_1,\sigma_2,\sigma_3,\sigma_4\} = Gal(K/\mathbb{Q}).$</p> <p>The following example might be hard to work out, but hopefully it is believable.</p> <p><em>Example/Exercise:</em> If $R(x) = x^3-2$, then the splitting field is the set \[L := \mathbb{Q}(\sqrt[3]{2},\omega) = \{a+b\sqrt[3]{2}+c\sqrt[3]{4}+d\omega+e\sqrt[3]{2}\omega+f\sqrt[3]{4}\omega|a,b,c,d,e,f \in \mathbb{Q}\}\] In this case, dimension of $L$ is 6. But there are exactly six permutations of 3 roots, so we know all the elements of the Galois group.</p> <p>At this point one must wonder, if the elements of the Galois group permute the roots of the polynomial $P(x)$, is it possible that some permutation transformations are not allowed? Let us revisit our examples.</p> <p><em>Example:</em> Recall the example of $Q(x) = x^4-10x^2 +1$. We see that $Gal(K/\mathbb{Q})$ has four elements. Let $r = \sqrt{2}+\sqrt{3}$, then we know that $[r]+[1/r]+[-r]+[-1/r]$ is the divisor of roots. Ideally 4 roots have 24 permutations possible. Since a field isomorphism respects arithmetic operations, if we define the isomorphism on $r$, it automatically determines the action of the rest! So we have only four possibilities. Indeed the Galois group has 4 elements: Send r to one of the roots.</p> <p>Any transformation that permutes roots is not necessarily an element of the Galois group. Sometimes the roots of a polynomial will have polynomial relations that may not be preserved by some transformations. These obstructions arise from polynomial relations between the roots.</p> <p><em>Example:</em> Consider the polynomial $S(x) = x^4-20x^2+80$ whose roots are \[\pm\sqrt{10\pm2\sqrt{5}}.\] Let us call $r = \sqrt{10+2\sqrt{5}},s=\sqrt{10-2\sqrt{5}}.$ Note that the roots of the polynomial are $\{r,s,-r,-s\}$. Any element of the Galois group permutes the roots. So is there an element of the Galois group that sends $(r,s)$ to $(s,r)$? Now we can argue that it is impossible. Suppose such an isomorphism exists. Then look at the relation \[rs(r^2-s^2)=80,\] applying $\sigma$ gives \[sr(s^2-r^2)=80\] which forces $80=-80$; a contradiction. A similar contradiction is obtained for transformations that send $(r,s)$ to $(-r,s)$ or $(r,-s)$ or $(-s,-r)$. However no contradiction is obtained from the equation $rs(r^2-s^2)=80$ for transformations that send $(r,s)$ to $(r,s),(-r,-s),(s,-r),(-s,r)$.</p> <p>Note that another identity is $r^2 -s^2 = rs$ which can also be used to get rid of certain permutations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="UG"/><category term="math"/><category term="algebra"/><category term="groups"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An example based understanding]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">INMO 24-25 Practice</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/INMO-Practice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="INMO 24-25 Practice"/><published>2025-01-01T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/INMO%20Practice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2025/INMO-Practice/"><![CDATA[<ol> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let ABCD be a trapezoid with BC parallel to AD and AB = CD. A circle ω centred at I is tangent to the segments AB, CD, and DA. The circle BIC meets the side AB at points B, and E. Prove that CE is tangent to ω.</span></p> <p><sup><em>Proof sketch:</em> $AB$ meet $CD$ at P. Let tangent from E meet $CD$ at C’. Incentre-Excentre lemma in triangle $PEC’$ says $\angle EIC’ = 90 - p/2$ where $p = \angle EPC’$. $BC || AD$ means $\angle EBC = 90+p/2$ and since $E,B,C,I$ are concyclic,$\angle EIC = 90 - p/2$. Thus angle EIC = angle EIC’ and thus C=C’.</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let ABC be an acute-angled triangle. The feet of the altitudes from A,B and C are D, E and F, respectively. Prove that DE+DF≤BC and determine the triangles for which equality holds.</span></p> <p><sup>Hint: Reflect F about BC to F’. Show E,D,F’ are collinear. Now consider circle with diameter BC and note that diameter is the longest chord.</sup></p> <p><sup>Another hint: trig kills the problem; use circle DEF is a nine-point circle, so get the radius.</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let O be the centre of the circumcircle ω of an acute-angle triangle ABC. A circle ω$_1$ with centre K passing through A, O and C and intersecting AB at M and BC at N . Point L is symmetric to K with respect to line NM. Prove that BL ⊥ AC. </span></p> <p><sup> <em>Proof sketch:</em> Show O is the orthocentre of triangle BMN. Circle (BMN) reflects about MN to $\omega_1$. So L is the centre of (BMN). OB is parallel to LK since both are perpendicular to MN and OK=LB since the segments are radii of reflected circles. Thus OBLK is a parallelogram and BL is parallel to OK. Now OK is perpendicular to AC since line joining centres is perpendicular to the common chord. Thus $BL \perp AC$. </sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let a,b,c and d denote the sides of a quadrilateral and m and n its diagonals. Prove that $mn\leq ac+bd,$ equality iff the quadrilateral is cyclic.</span></p> <p><sup> <em>Proof:</em> Let p,q,r,s be complex numbers associated to the vertices P,Q,R,S of the cyclic quadrilateral PQRS. Note that $(p-q)(r-s)+(q-r)(p-s) = (p-r)(q-s)$ and thus by triangle inequality we are done. Equality holds iff the ratio of summands is real and thus the cross-ratio is real (cyclicity condition). </sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let ABC be a triangle and AD,BE,CF be altitudes with H as orthocenter with D,E,F on sides. Suppose X is the intersection of circle passing through points A,E, F and the circumcircle of triangle ABC. Let EF meet BC at T. Show that A, T, X are collinear.</span></p> <p><sup><em>Hint:</em> Use inversion with centre A and radius $\sqrt{AH.AD}$. Note that the inversion exchanges B,D,C with F,H,E respectively. </sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let ABC be a triangle with orthocenter H and let D,E,F be the feet of the altitudes lying on the sides BC, CA, AB respectively. Let T=EF ∩ BC . Prove that TH is perpendicular to the A-median of triangle ABC.</span></p> <p><sup><em>Hint:</em> Use the previous problem to show H is the orthocentre of triangle ATM where M is the mid-point of BC.</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let AB be the diameter of a circle Γ and let C be a point on Γ different from A and B. Let D be the foot of perpendicular from C on to AB.Let K be a point on the segment CD such that AC is equal to the semi perimeter of ADK.Show that the excircle of ADK opposite A is tangent to Γ.</span></p> <p><sup><em>Hint:</em> Call the excircle of ADK opposite A as $\omega$. Invert about A with AC as radius. Now $\omega$ is orthogonal to $\Gamma$ and thus it is fixed under inversion. But $\Gamma$ is exchanged with line CD, so we are done. </sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let  E  and  F  be the midpoints on the respective sides  CA  and  AB  of triangle  ABC, and let  P  be the second point of intersection of the circles  ABE  and  ACF . Prove that the circle  AEF  intersects the line  AP  again in the point  X  for which  AX = 2XP .</span></p> <p><sup>A solution of the sample problem can be found <a href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Inversion/">here</a>.</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let the incircle of triangle ABC touch side BC at D , and let DT be a diameter of the circle. If line AT meets BC at X , then BD=CX .</span></p> <p><sup><em>Hint:</em> Show that a dilation that sends the incircle to the A-excircle sends T to the touchpoint of the excircle on BC. Then length chase.</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Let ABCD be a square. Let P be point inside the square such that PA = 1,PB = 2,PC = 3. Find ∠APB in degrees.</span> <sup> (Hint: Rotate about B by 90 degrees.)</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> ABCD is a unit square. Points P,Q,M,N are on sides AB, BC, CD, DA respectively such that AP + AN + CQ + CM = 2. Prove that PM⊥QN. </span> <sup>(Hint: Rotate by 90 degrees and spot a parallelogram.)</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Show that the composition of two rotations of angle magnitudes a and b, respectively around centres A and B, is equal to a rotation a + b around another centre X. This centre X is located at a position where ∠XAB = a/2 and ∠ABX = b/2.</span></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> (INMO 2024) Let points $A_1$ , $A_2$ and $A_3$ lie on the circle Γ in counter-clockwise order, and let P be a point in the same plane. For i ∈ {1,2,3} , let $τ_ i$ denote the counter-clockwise rotation of the plane centered at $A_ i$ , where the angle of the rotation is equal to the angle at vertex $A_i$ in $▵ A_1 A_2 A_3$ . Further, define $P_ i$ to be the point $τ_{i+2} ( τ_i ( τ_ {i+1} ( P ) ) )$ , where indices are taken modulo 3 (i.e., $τ_ 4 = τ_ 1$ and $τ_ 5 = τ_ 2$ ). Prove that the radius of the circumcircle of $▵ P_ 1 P_ 2 P_ 3$ is at most the radius of Γ . </span> <sup>Hint: Use the previous problem and show that $\triangle P_ 1 P_ 2 P_ 3$ is dilation of the contact triangle from point P by a factor of 2. Then use $R \geq 2r$)</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue"> Prove that:</span></p> <ol> <li><span style="color:blue"> the bisectors of the exterior angles of a triangle intersect the extensions of its opposite sides at three points lying on the same straight line;</span></li> <li><span style="color:blue"> the tangents drawn from the triangle’s vertices to the circle circumscribed about it intersect its opposite sides at three collinear points.</span></li> </ol> <p><sup> Hint: Menelaus theorem.</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue">In the plane let C be a circle, l a line tangent to the circle C and M a point on l . Find the locus of all points P with the following property: there exists two points Q,R on l such that M is the midpoint of QR and C is the inscribed circle of triangle PQR . </span></p> <p><sup><em>Hint:</em> Let T be the touchpoint of l and C, and let S be the diametrically opposite point to T in circle C. Locate X on l so that M is the midpoint of TX. Now use problem 9 above to argue that the locus of P is a segment of the line XS.</sup></p> </li> <li> <p><span style="color:blue">Let M be the midpoint of the arc ACB on the circumcircle of ▵ ABC , and let MD be the perpendicular to the longer of AC and BC , say AC . We will call D as the C -Archimedes point.</span></p> <ol> <li><span style="color:blue">Then show that D bisects the polygonal path ACB , that is, AD=DC+CB. (Archimedes theorem of broken chord.) </span></li> <li><span style="color:blue">Let P be the midpoint of AB , then show that DP is parallel to the C -angle bisector of triangle ACB .</span></li> <li><span style="color:blue">Suppose E,F are A -Archimedes point, B -Archimedes point of ▵ ABC , and Q,R are midpoints of BC and CA , respectively. Show that segments EQ,FR and DP concur.</span> <sup>(Hint: look at the medial triangle.) </sup></li> </ol> </li> </ol> <p><sup> Reference: See the first chapter of <a href="https://archive.org/details/episodes-in-nineteenth-and-twentieth-century-euclidean-geometry-ross-honsberger/page/n9/mode/2up">Ross Honsberger’s book</a> </sup></p> <ol> <li> <p><span style="color:blue">Let ABC be a triangle with AB&gt;AC . Let P be a point on the line AB beyond A such that AP+PC=AB . Let M be the mid-point of BC and let Q be the point on the side AB such that CQ⊥AM . Prove that BQ=2AP. <span></span></span></p> <p><sup>Hint: Use Archimedes broken chord. Point A’ outside line BP with PA’=PC, then angle A’CQ is right.</sup></p> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="teaching"/><category term="geometry"/><category term="INMO"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hints for INMOTC problems]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Inversion Problems</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Inversion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Inversion Problems"/><published>2024-12-08T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-08T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Inversion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Inversion/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>“One of the endearing things about mathematicians is the extent to which they will go to avoid doing any real work.” –Matthew Pordage</p> </blockquote> <p>In this blog post, we discuss the definition and properties of inversion, suggest a few configurations, outline the solution to a sample problem, and conclude with a few exercises.</p> <h1 id="inversion-a-recap">Inversion: A recap</h1> <p><em>Definition:</em> Given a circle $C$ with centre $O$ and radius $k$, the inversion of a point P ($\neq O$ ) in the plane is a point $P’$ on the ray $OP$ such that \[OP \times OP’ = k^2.\] <em>Facts:</em> If $C$ is a given circle, and $I_C$ represents the inversion of the plane (except $O$), then we have,</p> <ol> <li>A line $l$ through $O$ inverts to itself.</li> <li>A line $l$ not through $O$ inverts to a circle $l’$ passing through $O$ so that $l$ is the radical axis of $C$ and $l’$. Conversely a circle $\omega$ through $O$ inverts to a line $l$ not passing through $O$ so that $l$ is the radical axis of $\omega$ and $C$.</li> <li>A circle orthogonal to C inverts to itself.</li> <li>Given a circle $\omega$ not passing through $O$, inverts to a circle $\overline{\omega}$ not passing though $O$. The circle $\overline{\omega}$ can be obtained by dilating $\omega$ about $O$ with a dilation factor $\dfrac{k^2}{Pow_{\omega}(O)}.$</li> <li>Tangency is preserved under inversion.</li> </ol> <p>The following video series details the proofs of the above facts.</p> <iframe style="display: block; margin: auto;" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?si=R8xRcn2Kjbse2M_N&amp;list=PL2eijNv2W5mgDJcaPQBEl-B1H2dRtj84k" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <h1 id="configurations">Configurations</h1> <blockquote> <p>(Length formula) If A’,B’ are the inverse of A,B w.r.t a circle with centre O and radius $k$, show that the length of the segment A’B’ is \[A’B’ = k^2 \dfrac{AB}{OA \times OB}.\]</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof.</em> Use the fact that $ABB’A’$ is concyclic we get $\triangle OAB \sim \triangle OB’A’$. Using similarity ratios, we get \[\dfrac{OA}{OB’} = \dfrac{OB}{OA’}=\dfrac{AB}{A’B’} \] and thus \[A’B’ = \dfrac{k^2}{OA \times OB}AB.\]</p> <blockquote> <p>If P is outside the circle of inversion, then P’ is the midpoint of the chord of contact.</p> </blockquote> <p>There is a simple proof using similar triangles, but we will try to prove it using inversion.</p> <p><em>Proof.</em> Let A,B be touch points when tangents are drawn from $P$ to the circle of inversion. Note that the circle $\omega$ with $OP$ as diameter passes through A and B. So the circle $\omega$ inverts to the line AB. Define $P’:=OP \cap AB$ inverts to $OP \cap \omega = P(\neq O).$ So P is the inverse of P’. Note that P’ is the midpoint of AB since OP is the perpendicular bisector of AB (because $OA=OB$).</p> <blockquote> <p>Let ABC be a triangle with circumcircle Γ and contact triangle DEF . Consider an inversion with respect to the incircle of triangle ABC. Show that Γ is sent to the nine-point circle of triangle DEF.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof.</em> Note that E is on AB and F is on AC. By the previous problem the midpoint of EF is the inverse of A in the incircle. So the circumcircle passes through the midpoints of the sides of triangle DEF and is thus the nine-point circle of triangle DEF.</p> <blockquote> <p>Let ABC be a triangle. Consider the transformation consisting of an inversion about A with radius $k=\sqrt{AB\cdot AC}$ followed by a reflection around the angle bisector of $\angle BAC$. This transformation fixes B and C.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof.</em> Suppose $B,C \mapsto B’,C’$ under inversion, then \[ AB\cdot AB’ = k^2 = AB \cdot AC.\] Thus $AB’=AC$ and similarly $AC’ = AB$. If we reflect the plane about the A-angle bisector after the inversion then we have $B’,C’ \mapsto B’‘,C’’$, thus $AB’’ = AB$ with B’’ on AB, thus $B’‘=B$ and similarly $C’‘=C$.</p> <blockquote> <p>Let ABC be a triangle with circumcenter S. Invert around C with radius 1. What is the relation between S’, C, A’, and B’?</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof.</em> Using the length formula show that $S’A’ = A’C,S’B’=CB’.$ Thus $A’B’$ is the perpendicular bisector of $S’C’$.</p> <h1 id="a-sample-problem">A Sample Problem</h1> <blockquote> <p>Let  E  and  F  be the midpoints on the respective sides  CA  and  AB  of triangle  ABC, and let  P  be the second point of intersection of the circles  ABE  and  ACF . Prove that the circle  AEF  intersects the line  AP  again in the point  X  for which  AX = 2XP .</p> </blockquote> <p>Draw your own figure!</p> <p><em>Proof:</em>(Sketch) Invert the plane about $A$ with an arbitrary radius $k$. Circles $(AEBP),(AFPC), (AFXE)$ invert to lines $E’B’P’, F’P’C’,F’X’E’$. Note that the lines $AFB, AXP, AEC$ are fixed. Next we note that \[AE \times AE’ = AC \times AC’\] But $AC = 2AE$ since $E$ is midpoint of $AC$. Thus $C’$ is the midpoint of $AE’$. Similarly $B’$ is the midpoint of $AF’$. So we conclude $P’$ is the centroid of triangle $AF’E’$ and $X’$ is the midpoint of $F’E’$. Thus \[2AX’ = 3AP’ \implies 2 \dfrac{k^2}{AX} = 3 \dfrac{k^2}{AP} \implies 3AX = 2AP \implies AX = 2PX.\]</p> <h1 id="exercises">Exercises</h1> <ol> <li>For coplanar points $A, B, C, D,$ if they are concyclic, then show that \[AB·CD+AD·BC=AC·BD.\] (Hint: Length formula.)</li> <li>Let A, B, C be three collinear points and P be a point not on this line. Prove that the circumcenters of $\triangle PAB, \triangle PBC, \triangle PCA$ lie on a circle passing through P .</li> <li>(95 Iranian MO) Let M, N and P be points of intersection of the incircle of triangle ABC with sides AB, BC and CA respectively. Prove that the orthocenter of ∆MNP, the incenter of ∆ABC and the circumcenter of ∆ABC are collinear. (Hint: Consider Euler line of ∆MNP.)</li> <li>Let BC be a chord of a circle Γ. Let ω be a circle tangent to chord BC at K and internally tangent to ω at T. Then ray TK passes through the midpoint M of the arc BC not containing T.</li> <li>Let $P$ be a point inside triangle ABC such that $\angle APB − \angle ACB = \angle APC − \angle ABC$. Let $D, E$ be the incenters of triangles $APB,APC,$ respectively. Show that $AP,BD,CE$ meet at a point. (Hint: invert about $A$.)</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="teaching"/><category term="geometry"/><category term="INMO"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Inversion is reflection in a circle.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RMO 2024 Sketches</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/RMO-2024-solution-sketches/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RMO 2024 Sketches"/><published>2024-11-03T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-03T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/RMO-2024-solution-sketches</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/RMO-2024-solution-sketches/"><![CDATA[<p>I solved the RMO problems today after the exam. I am documenting the solutions and my feelings of difficulty (out of 5) for each problem. I hope you enjoy the solutions. Let me know if you liked it, and share the solutions with interested people.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241103231432.png" alt="Problem 1"/></p> <p><em>RMO difficulty feeling:</em> <b>1</b>.</p> <p>Straightforward problem. The invariant of part a is standard. The second part is not too convoluted and is something most people will try. It’s a good beginner problem that sets the mood and eases the participant.</p> <p><em>Proof:</em></p> <p>(a) Suppose n is odd and $a_1,a_2,\ldots a_n$ is a nice rearrangement. Since $a_1,a_2,\ldots a_n$ is a permutation of $1,2,3,\ldots,n$ it is immediate that \[a_1 + a_2 + a_3 +\ldots + a_n = 1+2+3+\ldots+n=\frac{n(n+1)}2.\] Since $n$ is odd, we note that $n(n+1)/2$ is a multiple of $n$ since $n+1$ is even. This contradicts the niceness of the rearrangement since $a_1 + a_2 + a_3 +\ldots + a_n$ is a multiple of $n$.</p> <p>(b) If n is even, we claim <em>the rearrangement $2,1,4,3,6,5,8,7,….n,n-1$ is always nice</em>.</p> <p>The proof is by induction on $n$. For $n=2$, clearly $2,1$ is nice since 2 does not divide 3. Suppose we have proved the claim for some even n, then we show the claim holds for n+2. For n+2, we already know $a_1 + a_2 + a_3 +\ldots + a_k$ is not a multiple of k for $k \leq n$ by induction. Next we note that $a_1+\ldots+a_{n+1} = n(n+1)/2 + (n+1)+1$ which leaves a remainder of 1 when divided by $n+1$ since the first two terms are multiples of $n+1$. And finally \[a_1 + a_2 + a_3 +\ldots + a_{n+2} = \frac{(n+2)(n+3)}{2}.\] The number $\frac{(n+2)(n+3)}{2}$ is not divisible by $n+2$ since the quotient $\frac{(n+3)}{2}$ is a fraction (because n+3 is odd). Thus $a_1 + a_2 + a_3 +\ldots + a_{n+2}$ is not a multiple of $n+2$. Thus the claim is proved for $n+2$. So the proof of the statement “the rearrangement $2,1,4,3,6,5,8,7,….n,n-1$ is always nice” is complete.</p> <hr/> <p><img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241103233834.png" alt="Problem 2"/> <em>RMO difficulty feeling:</em> <b>2</b>.</p> <p>Straightforward to guess the answer by trial and error. But proving it requires you to note that $R(n) &gt; n$ eventually. Now $R(n)$ grows as $n^2$ so there will be many ways to do this proof. The proof writing is the main focus of this question since the idea is pretty simple. It’s rated 2 because of the algebra can get messy for a beginner.</p> <p><em>Proof:</em> The key idea is to note that by division algorithm if $a,b$ are natural numbers, then \[a = \left\lfloor \frac{a}{b} \right\rfloor b+ r\] where r is the remainder when a is divided by b. So we have a formula for $R(n)$: \[ R(n) = \sum_{k=1}^n \left(n - \left\lfloor\frac{n}{k}\right\rfloor k\right)\] We note that for $n \geq k &gt; n/2$, we have $1 \leq \frac{n}{k} &lt; 2$. Thus $\lfloor n/k\rfloor = 1$ for this range. The terms in this range are summable and we thus obtain a bound for all $n$: \[R(n) \geq \sum_{k &gt; \lceil n/2\rceil}^n (n-k) = 1+ 2 +\ldots + \left(\lceil n/2 \rceil -1\right) \geq \dfrac{n/2(n/2-1)}{2} = \dfrac{n(n-2)}{8}.\] In the problem, we want to solve for $R(n) = n-1$. Suppose $m$ solves the equation, then \[m-1 = R(m) \geq \dfrac{m(m-2)}{8}.\] Thus we solve the quadratic inequality to get \[8m-8 \geq m^2-2m \implies m^2 -10m + 8 \leq 0 \implies m \leq 9.\] Thus we have to check the first 9 numbers only. We see \[R(1)=0, R(2)=0, R(3)=1, R(4)=1, R(5)=4,R(6)=3,R(7)=8, R(8)=8, R(9)=12,\] thus $1,5$ are the only solutions.</p> <hr/> <p><img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241104001206.png" alt="Problem 3"/></p> <p><em>RMO difficulty feeling:</em> <b>3</b>.</p> <p>I wonder if there is a synthetic solution. All the lengths in the problem make it clear that most solutions will mostly be length bash based. Since there is a busy right angled point (D), it is suitable for a coordinate bash. Sophisticated coordinates computation is not a part of school syllabus and further one should either know various facts or compute heavily to get the relation between coordinates and figure out $a^2=24$.</p> <p><em>Proof:</em> The proof is a straightforward coordinate computation. <em>We have labelled the circumcentre as S instead of O</em>. Look at the diagram below where S, G, I, H are the circumcentre, centroid, incentre and orthocentre of triangle $ABC$, respectively. <img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241104001528.png" alt="Figure for problem 3" width="350" style="display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto"/></p> <p>Note that $G=\left(0,\dfrac{a}3\right).$ It is well known that G trisects the segment SH (often proved as a part of the Euler line theorem), we have \[2(0,s)+(0,h) = 3(0,a/3)\] and thus $2s+h=a$. It is given in the problem that $2|DS| = 23|HD|$ and thus $2s=23h$. So we have \[h = \frac{a}{24}, \,\, 2s = \frac{23a}{24}.\] Since $S$ is the circumcentre, we must have $|SA|=|SB|$ and thus \[(s-a)^2 = s^2+1.\] Rearranging we get \[a^2-2as = 1 \implies a^2 - (23a^2/24) = 1 \implies a^2 = 24.\] Now this means we compute sidelengths \[|AB|=|AC| = \sqrt{a^2+1}= 5, \,\, |BC|=2.\] Using the angle bisector lemma, we can say that I divides $AD$ in the ratio $|AB|:|BD|=5:1$ and thus \[\dfrac{|AI|}{|ID|} = 5 \implies I = \dfrac{5(0,0)+1(0,a)}{6}=\left(0,\dfrac{a}6\right).\]Since $ID \perp BC$, $D$ is a touch point of the incircle with line $BC$.So $D$ lies on the incircle and the line $ID$ is a diameter. Since $G$ lies on the line $ID$, in order to show $G$ is on the incircle, it suffices to show $GD$ is a diameter. So we show that $I$ is the midpoint of $GD$. Let $M$ be the midpoint of $GD$, \[M = (G+D)/2 = (\left(0,\frac{a}3\right)+(0,0))/2 = \left(0,\frac{a}6\right) = I.\] So $G$ lies on the incircle of $\triangle ABC$.</p> <hr/> <p><img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241104064438.png" alt="Problem 4"/></p> <p><em>RMO difficulty feeling:</em> <b>5</b>.</p> <p>I think this is the hardest problem in the set. In the solution, I will leave algebraic manipulation to the reader since it is boring to watch other people do algebra. While I finished the rest of the paper in 75 minutes, this problem alone took over an hour! I generally try brute forcing algebra only when I am at my wits’ end. Brute forcing the algebra worked here and it was not all that hard. The hardness is due to the fact that none of the standard inequalities like AM-GM, Cauchy-Schwarz worked when I tried. Adding the inequalities was weak. Adding them in batches failed too. It needed raw thinking and no theorems helped me. So its a 5 in my heart.</p> <p><em>Proof:</em> We will prove the inequality by contradiction. In fact we will contradict the constraint \[a_1^2+a_2^2+a_3^2+a_4^2=1.\]Without loss of generality, assume $a_4 \leq a_3 \leq a_2 \leq a_1$. Suppose for all $1\leq i &lt; j \leq 4$, \[(a_i-a_j)^2 &gt; \frac15.\] Thus we have \[ a_1-a_2 &gt; \frac1{\sqrt{5}},a_2-a_3 &gt; \frac1{\sqrt{5}}, a_3-a_4 &gt; \frac1{\sqrt{5}}. \] Now set \[a_1-a_2-\frac1{\sqrt{5}}=x,\] \[ a_2-a_3-\frac1{\sqrt{5}}=y,\] \[a_3-a_4 -\frac1{\sqrt{5}} =z,\] and note that $x,y,z &gt; 0$. Rearranging and back-substituting the variables we get \[a_3 = a_4 + \frac1{\sqrt{5}} + z,\] \[a_2 = a_4 + \frac2{\sqrt{5}} + y+z,\] \[a_1 = a_4 + \frac3{\sqrt{5}} + x+y+z.\]</p> <p>Now <em>it can be shown that</em> (meaning you should do some work!) \[a_1^2 +a_2^2+a_3^2 + a_4^2 = \left(2a_4+\dfrac{3x+2y+z+\dfrac{6}{\sqrt{5}}}{2}\right)^2 + 1 + \dfrac{3x^2}4+y^2+\frac{3z^2}4 + xy+yz+\dfrac{xz}2+\dfrac{3x+4y+3z}{\sqrt{5}}.\]The expression on the right-hand side is greater one, since $x,y,z &gt; 0$, which contradicts the given constraint.</p> <hr/> <p><img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241104070926.png" alt="Problem 5"/></p> <p><em>RMO difficulty feeling:</em> <b>1.5</b>.</p> <p>It’s a pleasant and straightforward problem, once you realise that you can do it by trigonometry. A single cyclic quadrilateral with angle conditions is usually a poster boy for trigonometry problems.</p> <p>The problem is pretty cute, though, and I will include it as an application of the sine rule in my geometry courses. The proof is straightforward once you have chased angles. I like cute and sweet problems in the Olympiad.</p> <p><em>Proof:</em> We proceed by trigonometry and sine rule. Let $R$ be the radius of the circle. Consider the following figure, which has angles marked. <img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241104071800.png" alt="Problem 5 diagram" width="450" style="display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto"/> We have used the parallel lines to mark alternate angles equal and we have also used angles in the same segment are equal. We have to show \[OB(AB+CD) = OL(AC+BD).\] First we note that $OL = R \cos \alpha$ by applying the definition of $\cos \alpha$ in $\triangle AOL$. Using extended sine rule, we have to show \[R(2R\sin (2\alpha+\beta) + 2R\sin \beta) = R\cos \alpha (2R \sin (\alpha + \beta)+ 2R \sin (\alpha+\beta)).\] which reduces to proving</p> <p>\[\sin (2\alpha + \beta) + \sin \beta = 2 \cos \alpha \sin (\alpha+\beta).\] But this simply follows from applying $\sin x + \sin y = 2\sin \left(\dfrac{x+y}{2}\right)\cos \left(\dfrac{x-y}{2}\right).$</p> <hr/> <p><img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241104073545.png" alt="Problem 5"/></p> <p><em>Comment:</em> My student Rishon Fernandes pointed to me that this problem is a subproblem of British Math Olympiad 2022 Round 1, Problem 5.</p> <p><em>RMO difficulty feeling:</em> 3.</p> <p>Nice problem. This problem is asking for the number of chains in a divisor lattice. In fact if $f(n)$ denotes the number of chains of divisors of $n$, then one can easily prove the recursion \[2f(n) = \sum_{d \mid n} f(d).\] I thought Mobius inversion and the associated techniques will be useful. I like the question since it is steeped in Lattice theory and it is asking for a special case. So it has room for exploration and tingles the scientist in me.</p> <p>As a RMO problem, either you had to set-up a recursion, or solve it by bijecting it to some associated problem like I did in my solution below. There are many lines of attack and all of them involve some careful computation. Since it has many approaches, my difficulty feeling is lower. The difficulty rating is still 3 since writing a clear solution is tricky and the use of the bijection/recursion to get to the answer is non-trivial.</p> <p>Proof: We write the divisors of $3\cdot 2^m$ in the form of a diagram shown below (ignore the colors for now). In the diagram, if there is a path from a to b, then a divides b . <img src="/assets/img/Pasted image 20241104074433.png" alt="Hasse Diagram" width="650" style="display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto"/></p> <p>A maximal chain is a chain that cannot be enlarged by including an divisors. Every chain is contained in a maximal chain and every maximal chain has length $m+2$. In the directed graph shown, a maximal chain is a directed path starting from 1 and ending at $3\cdot2^m$. Since 1 is on the top and $3.2^m$ is on the bottom, a directed path must switch from top to bottom exactly once (since in this graph, we cant go up once we are on the bottom row). Suppose the switch happens at $3\cdot 2^k$ as shown in the figure, for $k=0,1,2,\cdots,m$.</p> <p>For $k \neq m$, any chain that is a part of this maximal chain contains 1, $3\cdot 2^k$, $3\cdot 2^m$ and we are free to choose a subset of the remaining $m-1$ elements (colored red in the figure). The number of subsets is $2^{m-1}$. Thus we have m choices for $k$ (since $k \neq m$) which gives $m$ maximal chains , and $2^{m-1}$ chains that are a subset of each of these maximal chains, we have $m\cdot 2^{m-1}$ choices.</p> <p>For $k=m$, we have to find the subsets of chains on the top row. Since there are $m$ terms from 2 to $2^m$, we have $2^m$ chains in this case.</p> <p>So totally we have $m\cdot 2^{m-1} + 2^m = (m+2)2^{m-1}$ chains.</p> <hr/> <p>I liked solving the problems and it was balanced for an RMO. I am suspecting the cut-off is upwards of 50 points since 3 problems were doable by standard problem solving techniques. I think it will be less that 70 since I think very few students will get upwards of 4 problems. I will update this post once the actual cutoff is released.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="solving"/><category term="rmo"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts, Outline and Comments]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inequalities from Engel’s Olympiad book.</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Arthur-Engel's-Inequality-problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inequalities from Engel’s Olympiad book."/><published>2024-11-02T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-02T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Arthur-Engel&apos;s-Inequality-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Arthur-Engel&apos;s-Inequality-problems/"><![CDATA[<p>The following tips are from Arthur Engel’s book:</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/Screenshot 2024-11-02 at 10.14.49 AM.png" alt="Engel's tips" width="550" style="display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto"/></p> <blockquote> <p>Prove that for any triangle with sides $a,b,c$ and area $A$, \(a^2 + b^2 + c^2 \geq 4\sqrt{3}A.\)</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof:</em> We will write down the steps and explain it below: \[a^2 + b^2 +c^2 \geq ab+bc+ca = \dfrac{2A}{\sin C}+\dfrac{2A}{\sin A}+\dfrac{2A}{\sin B} \geq \dfrac{18A}{\sin A + \sin B + \sin C} \geq \dfrac{36A}{3\sqrt{3}} = 4\sqrt{3}A.\] Equality iff $a=b=c$.</p> <p>The explanations for each step</p> <ol> <li> <p>First inequality follows from applying AM-GM to the sets $\{a^2,b^2\},\{b^2,c^2\},\{c^2,a^2\}$ and adding the inequalities.</p> </li> <li> <p>The first equality follows from the area formula in terms of sines.</p> </li> <li> <p>The second inequality follows from AM-HM.</p> </li> <li> <p>The third inequality follows from Jensen’s inequality applied to sin A, sin B and sin C noting that sin is concave in $[0,\pi]$ and $A+B+C=\pi$.</p> </li> </ol> <p>Remark: There are five other proofs of this fact in Engel’s problem solving strategies.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>In triangle ABC, the angle bisectors $AD, BE, CF$ meet at $I$. Show that \[\dfrac14 &lt; \dfrac{IA}{AD}\cdot \dfrac{IB}{BE} \cdot \dfrac{IC}{CF} \leq \dfrac{8}{27}.\]</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof:</em> By angle bisector theorem, we see that \[\dfrac{IA}{ID} = \dfrac{b+c}{a}\] and thus \[\dfrac{AI}{AD} = \dfrac{b+c}{a+b+c}.\] So we have to show \[\dfrac14 &lt; \dfrac{(b+c)(a+b)(c+a)}{(a+b+c)^3}\leq \dfrac{8}{27}.\] The upper bound follows from applying AM-GM to $a+b,b+c,c+a$.</p> <p>For the lower bound, define $x = a+b-c, y=b+c-a, z=c+a-b$ and note that $2a = x+z, 2b=x+y, 2c=y+z.$ By triangle inequality, we note that $x,y,z&gt;0.$ Since the inequality is homogenous, we will normalise and impose the constraint $a+b+c=1$ which implies $x+y+z=1$.</p> <p>Thus we have \[ \dfrac{(b+c)(a+b)(c+a)}{(a+b+c)^3} = (1-a)(1-b)(1-c) = \dfrac{(2-x-z)(2-x-y)(2-y-z)}8\]</p> <p>\[= \dfrac{(1+y)(1+z)(1+x)}{8} =\dfrac{(1+x+y+z+ xy+yz+zx+xyz)}{8} &gt; \dfrac28 = \dfrac14.\]</p> <hr/> <p>Here are some practice problems from Arthur Engel’s book:</p> <ol> <li> <p>For positive reals $a,b,c,d$ show that \[\sqrt{ab} + \sqrt{cd} \leq \sqrt{(a+d)(b+c)}.\]</p> </li> <li> <p>If $a,b,c &gt;0$ then prove that at least one of the expression $a(1-b),b(1-c),c(1-a)$ is less than or equal to $\frac14$.</p> </li> <li> <p>Prove the inequality \[(a^3-a+2)^2 &gt; 4a^2 (a^2+1)(a-2).\]</p> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="solving"/><category term="algebra"/><category term="inequality"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Inequality problems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RMO Algebra Prep</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Algebra-RMO-prep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RMO Algebra Prep"/><published>2024-10-10T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Algebra-RMO-prep</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Algebra-RMO-prep/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>(BMO 2005) Find the minimum possible value of $x^2 + y^2$ given that x and y are real numbers with $x \neq 0$, satisfying \[xy( x^2 − y^2 ) = x^2 + y^2.\]</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Solution:</em> Put $x=r\cos\theta$, $y=r\sin\theta$. We are supposed to minimize $r^2$ and the constraint reduces to \[r^2 \sin 4\theta = 4.\] So $r^2$ is minimized when $\sin 4\theta = 1.$ Thus the minimum value of $r^2$ is $4$.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>[BMO 2008] Find all real values of $x, y$ and $z$ such that<br/> \[(x+1)yz = 12\] \[(y+1)zx=4\] \[(z+1)xy = 4\]</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Solution(Mrinal).</em> We begin by subtracting (2) from (3), which yields \[x(y-z)=0.\] Clearly $x \neq 0$ as it would not satisfy the last two equations, and thus $y=z$. We proceed by subtracting (2) from (1), and adding (2) and (3), yielding \[y(y-x)=2xy(y+1)=8.\] Thus $x = \frac{4}{y(y+1)}$. Substituting this into the above, we get</p> \[\\ \begin{aligned} y\left(y-\dfrac{4}{y(y+1)}\right)&amp;=8. \\ y^3+y^2-8y-12&amp;=0, \\ (y+2)^2(y-3)&amp;=0. \end{aligned} \\\] <p>Thus, the required solution sets are $(x, y, z) = (2, -2, -2) \ \text{and} \ \left(\frac{1}{3}, 3, 3\right).$</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>(BMO 1993) Let x,y,z be positive real numbers satisfying $\frac{1}{3} \leq xy+yz+zx \leq 3$ . Determine the range of values for xyz and x+y+z.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof(Rishon,Abhhi,Srikanth):</em> <strong>We claim the range of $xyz$ is $(0,1]$.</strong> Let $\alpha &gt; 0$ be a real. We choose $x=\alpha,y=z=\frac1{\alpha}$ then we see that $xy+yx+xz = 2+\frac1{\alpha^2}$ which satisfies the given inequality for $\alpha \geq 1$. Now \[xyz = \frac1{\alpha}.\] Note that for any real $r \in (0,1]$, $\alpha = \frac1{r}$ will give $xyz=r$. So we are done.</p> <p><strong>We claim the range of $x+y+z$ is $[1,\infty)$.</strong> By applying AM-GM to $x^2+y^2,y^2+z^2,x^2+z^2$ we see that \[x^2+y^2 + z^2 \geq xy + yz + xz.\]</p> <p>This is equivalent to $(x+y+z)^2 \geq 3(xy+yz+xz) \geq 1$ . Since $x,y,z &gt; 0$ we conclude $x+y+z \geq 1.$ Equality can be achieved for $x=y=z=\frac13,$ which is also satisfied by the given inequality (in the problem statement).</p> <p>We will show that all the values above 1 will be achieved using <em>intermediate value theorem</em> (which can be found at the end of this solution).</p> <p>If we choose $x=\frac13 + r,y=\frac13,z=\frac13$, then we see that \[xy+yx+xz = \frac{2r+1}3 .\] The given inequality reduces to $0\leq r \leq 4.$ Thus we see that the range of $x+y+z = 1+r$ is $[1,5]$ for $0\leq r \leq 4.$</p> <p>Let $\alpha &gt; 0$ be a real. Next we take $x=\alpha,y=z=\frac1{\alpha}$ then we see that $xy+yx+xz = 2+\frac1{\alpha^2}$ which satisfies the given inequality for $\alpha \geq 1$. Now \[x+y+z = \alpha + \frac{2}{\alpha} \geq 2\sqrt{2}.\] The last inequality is by AM-GM and equality is achieved at $\alpha = \sqrt{2}$. Now since $f(\alpha) = \alpha + \frac{2}{\alpha}$ is a continuous unbounded function, by IMVT its range is $[2\sqrt{2},\infty)$ .</p> <p>Thus we conclude $[1,5] \cup [2\sqrt{2},\infty)=[1,\infty)$ is the range of $x+y+z$.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="appendix-to-problem-1">Appendix to Problem 1:</h3> <p><u>(Intermediate Value Theorem/IMVT)</u> Let $f:[a,b] \to \mathbb{R}$ be a continuous function. If $\lambda$ is between $f(a), f(b)$ then there is an $x \in (a,b)$ such that $f(x) = \lambda$.</p> <p>We shall also use the fact that sum, difference, product and quotient (as long as denominator does not vanish) of continuous functions are continuous. Additionally, polynomials are continuous functions.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>(BMO 2004) Let S be a set of rational numbers with the following properties:</p> <ol> <li>$\frac12 \in S$</li> <li>If x ∈ S , then both $\frac1{x+1} \in S$ and $\frac{x}{x+1} \in S$.</li> </ol> <p>Prove that S contains all rational numbers in the interval 0&lt;x&lt;1 .</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof(Rishon):</em> The proof is by strong induction on the denominator of a rational number between 0 and 1. The base case is $n=2$ and the only fraction with denominator 2 is $\frac12$. It is given that S contains this fraction.<br/> Suppose we have shown that all rational numbers, in their simplest form with denominator strictly less than $n$, are in $S$. We break the calculation into three cases:</p> <p><u>Case 1:</u> If $k &lt; n/2$, then $k &lt; n-k$. Now \[\dfrac{k}{n-k}\in S \implies \dfrac{k}{n}=\dfrac{\frac{k}{n-k}}{\frac{k}{n-k}+1} \in S\] <u>Case 2:</u> If $k &gt; n/2$, then $k &gt; n-k$. Again we see \[\dfrac{n-k}{k}\in S \implies \dfrac{k}{n}=\dfrac{1}{\frac{n-k}{k}+1} \in S.\] <u>Case 3:</u> If $k = n/2$, then \[\dfrac{k}{n} = \dfrac12 \] which is in $S$ by the hypothesis of the problem. So we are done.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>(BMO R2 2019) Find all functions $f$ from the positive real numbers to the positive real numbers for which $f( x ) \leq f( y )$ whenever $x \leq y$ and \[f( x^4 ) +f( x^2 ) +f( x ) +f( 1 ) = x^4 + x^2 +x+1.\] for all $x&gt;0$.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof (Rishon, Lauren, Abhhi and Srikanth):</em> Clearly $f(1)=1.$ If we define $g(x) = f(x) - x$, then we see $g(x^4)+g(x^2)+g(x)=0.$ But $x=y,x=y^2$ and subtract to get \[g(y^8) = g(y)\] for all real $y &gt; 0$. Note that this means \[\displaystyle g(x^{8^n}) =g(x)=g(x^{\frac1{8^n}})\] for all $n$ and for all $x&gt;0$.</p> <p>Now we show that $g\equiv0$, by analysing two cases.</p> <p><u>Case 1:</u> For $x &lt; 1$, since $g(1)=0$, and the non-decreasing nature of $f$ we get: \[g(x) + x \leq g(1)+1 = 1\] Now we note that $x^{\frac1{8^n}}&lt;1$ since $x&lt;1$. So \[g(x) + x^{\frac1{8^n}} = g(x^{\frac1{8^n}}) + x^{\frac1{8^n}} \leq 1.\] Thus $g(x) \leq 1 - x^{\frac1{8^n}}$ for all $n$. By applying $lim_{n \to \infty}$ on both sides and noting $\lim_{n\to \infty} x^{\frac1{8^n}} = 1$ for $x&gt;0$, we get \[g(x) \leq 0.\]If $x&lt;1$, then $x^2,x^4 &lt; 1$. So $g(x^4),g(x^2),g(x)\leq 0$. But $g(x^4)+g(x^2)+g(x)=0$ and thus each term is individually zero. So we conclude $g(x) = 0$ for $0 &lt; x &lt; 1$.</p> <p><u>Case 2:</u> For $x &gt; 1$, since $g(1)=0$, \[g(x) + x \geq 1\] Now we note that $x^{\frac1{8^n}}&gt;1$ since $x&gt;1$. So \[g(x) + x^{\frac1{8^n}} = g(x^{\frac1{8^n}}) + x^{\frac1{8^n}} \geq 1.\] Thus $g(x) \geq 1 - x^{\frac1{8^n}}$ for all $n$. By applying $\displaystyle \lim_{n \to \infty}$ on both sides and noting $\displaystyle \lim_{n\to \infty} x^{\frac1{8^n}} = 1$ for $x&gt;0$, we get \[g(x) \geq 0.\] If $x&gt;1$, then $x^2,x^4 &gt; 1$. So $g(x^4),g(x^2),g(x)\geq 0$. But $g(x^4)+g(x^2)+g(x)=0$ and thus each is individually zero. So we conclude $g(x) = 0$ for $x &gt;1$.</p> <p>Thus we have showed that $g\equiv0$.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>(RMO 2017) Let $x, y, z$ be real numbers, each greater than 1. Prove that \[\dfrac{x+1}{y+1} + \dfrac{y+1}{z+1} + \dfrac{z+1}{x+1} \leq \dfrac{x-1}{y-1} + \dfrac{y-1}{z-1} + \dfrac{z-1}{x-1}.\]</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof(Mrinal).</em> Let us assume that $x \geq y \geq z$. We are to show that \[\sum_{cyc} \left(\dfrac{x-1}{y-1}-\dfrac{x+1}{y+1}\right) = \sum_{cyc} \left( \dfrac{x-y}{y^2-1} \right) \geq 0.\] Begin by calling the latter quantity $G$. Since $x \geq y \geq z$, we have \[G=\dfrac{x-y}{y^2-1}+\dfrac{y-z}{z^2-1}+\dfrac{z-y+y-x}{x^2-1}.\] This is equivalent to \[G=(y-z)\left( \dfrac{1}{z^2-1}-\dfrac{1}{x^2-1}\right)+(x-y)\left( \dfrac{1}{y^2-1}-\dfrac{1}{x^2-1}\right).\] Since $x \geq y, y \geq z$ and $x \geq z$, each expression bounded by paranthesis is non-negative. So we conclude that $G \geq 0$, and we are done. A similar proof is needed for $x \geq z \geq y$ which we leave to the reader.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>(RMO 2017) Let $P(x)=x^2+\frac{1}{2}x+b$ and $Q(x)=x^2+cx+d$ be two polynomials with real coefficients such that $P(x)Q(x)=Q(P(x))$ for all real $x$. Find all the real roots of $P(Q(x))=0.$</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Claim:</em> The only real roots are $-1$ and $\frac12$.</p> <p><em>Proof (Mrinal).</em> The given condition is equivalent to \[\left(x^2+\dfrac{x}{2}+b\right)\left(x^2+cx+d \right)=\left( x^2+\dfrac{x}{2} +b\right)^2+c\left( x^2+\dfrac{x}{2}+b\right)+d.\] We now proceed by comparing coefficients of $x^3, x^2$ and constants of both sides (comparing coeffient of $x$ is redundant).</p> <ol> <li> <p>Comparing the coefficient of $x^3$ gives \[c+\dfrac{1}{2}=1 \implies c=\dfrac{1}{2}.\]</p> </li> <li> <p>Comparing the coefficient of $x^2$ gives \[d+\dfrac{c}{2}+b=\dfrac{1}{4}+2b+c.\] On substituting $c=\frac12$, we get \[d=\dfrac{1}{2}+b.\]</p> </li> <li> <p>Comparing constants, we get \[bd=b^2+\dfrac{b}{2}+d.\] Substituting $d=\frac12 + b$, we get $d=0, b=-\frac{1}{2}.$</p> </li> </ol> <p>We now set $P(Q(x))=0$ as follows.</p> \[\\ \begin{aligned} \left( x^2+\dfrac{x}{2} \right)^2+\dfrac{1}{2}\left( x^2+\dfrac{x}{2} \right)-\dfrac{1}{2}&amp;=0 \\ 4x^4+4x^3+3x^2+x-2&amp;=0. \end{aligned} \\\] <p>On inspection, we see that $(x+1)$ is a factor of the above. Performing long division yields \[4x^4+4x^3+3x^2+x-2=(x+1)(4x^3+3x-2).\] Again, by inspection, we see that $(2x-1)$ is a factor, giving us the final factorisation of \[4x^4+4x^3+3x^2+x-2=(x+1)(2x-1)(2x^2+x+2).\] Since the quadratic has no real roots, we conclude that the only real roots are $-1$ and $\frac{1}{2}$.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="solving"/><category term="Olympiad"/><category term="algebra"/><category term="inequality"/><category term="fe"/><category term="bmo"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Algebra problems from bmo.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can the given expression equal a perfect square?</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Perfect-square-Olympiad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can the given expression equal a perfect square?"/><published>2024-10-08T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Perfect-square-Olympiad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Perfect-square-Olympiad/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>“I fear not the man who has practised 10,000 kicks once, but I fear the man who has practised one kick 10,000 times.”</p> <p>- Bruce Lee</p> </blockquote> <p><img src="/assets/img/Bruceleeperfectsquare.png" alt="Kick quadratic" width="350" style="display:block; margin-left:auto; margin-right:auto"/></p> <p>Certain classes of problem-solving strategies repeatedly prove helpful in many Olympiads worldwide. In today’s blog post, we will discuss some strategies for the following type of problem:</p> <blockquote> <p>Find all integers $n$ such that a quadratic expression $f(n)$ (or $f(n,m,\ldots)$) is a perfect square.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>There are usually two strategies that are used to claim no solutions exist:</em></p> <ul> <li>Using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadratic_residue">quadratic residues</a>, argue that there are no solutions. For instance, $12m+ 19$ can never be a perfect square since it is for the form $4k+3$ and we know that 3 is not a quadratic residue modulo 4.</li> <li>Bound the given expressions between two consecutive perfect squares. For instance, $n^2 +n+1$ can be bounded as follows: \[n^2 &lt; n^2+n + 1&lt; (n+1)^2.\] But there cannot be a perfect square between two consecutive perfect square numbers. So $n^2 +n+1$ cannot be a perfect square.</li> </ul> <p><em>There are usually two (related) strategies that are used to find solutions:</em></p> <ul> <li>Complete the squares and factorise using algebraic identities (usually $x^2 - y^2$). Sometimes, we can find a bound on the variables and brute force our way through. If the perfect square is factored into co-prime factors, each factor itself must be a perfect square. We will then get a system of equations to solve.</li> <li>We can use the quadratic root formula and determine when the discriminant is a perfect square.</li> </ul> <p>Following Lee’s advice, I suggest you practice many problems using the techniques discussed. Let me show you some of these kicks once. If you want to see other kicks, comment below (you need a Github account to comment). I will include them.</p> <h2 id="factoring-and-bounding-kicks">Factoring and bounding kicks</h2> <p>The following British Maths Olympiad problem can be solved in multiple ways. Enjoy the kicks.</p> <blockquote> <p>(BMO R1 2011) Find all integers $n$ for which $n^2 +20n+11$ is a perfect square.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof 1</em>: We claim that $n=35,-55$ are the only solutions. We proceed by completing the square. We must solve for $n$ in the following equation: \[(n+10)^2-89=k^2.\] Now $(n+10)^2 - k^2 =89$ and thus $(n+10-k)(n+10+k)=89$ . Since $89$ is prime, we get a couple of cases. <strong>Case 1:</strong> ${n+10-k,n+10+k}={1,89}$. By adding and simplifying, we get $n=35$. <strong>Case 2:</strong> ${n+10-k,n+10+k}={-1,-89}$. By adding and simplifying, we get $n=-55$.</p> <hr/> <p><em>Proof 2:(Abhhi and Rishon)</em> Let $N = n^2 + 20n + 11$. We will find solutions by repeatedly bounding $N$ between two consecutive squares.</p> <p>We note that for $n&gt; 35$, since $0 &lt; 2n-70$, by adding $n^2 + 18n + 81$ to both sides we see that $(n+9)^2 &lt; n^2 +20n + 11$. On the other hand, $n^2 + 20n + 11 &lt; n^2 + 20 n + 100$. Thus we have for $n &gt; 35$, \[(n+9)^2 &lt; n^2 + 20n + 11 &lt; (n+10)^2.\] Since $N$ is bounded between two consecutive squares, it cannot be a perfect square. For $n=35$, we see that $N= 44^2$. For $13 &lt; n &lt; 35$, we similarly bound $N$ again as \[(n+8)^2 &lt; n^2 + 20n + 11 &lt; (n+9)^2.\] Indeed, the lower bound reduces to $4n &gt; 53$ which holds for $n &gt; 13$ and the upper bound simplifies to $n &lt; 35$. So we have bounded $N$ between two consecutive squares again, and thus, N cannot be a perfect square. Now $n=13$ is not a solution since $N=440$ is a non-square number. Repeating the bounding trick, we can check that \[(n+7)^2 &lt; n^2 + 20n + 11 &lt; (n+8)^2\] holds for $6 &lt; n &lt; 13$ and conclude that $N$ is not a perfect square. Finally, if we plugin $n \in \{1,2,3,4,5,6\}$ we get $N \in \{32,55,80,107,136,167\}$. None of these values of $N$ are perfect squares. So we are done.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Comments:</strong> We note that Proof 1 simplified because $89$ had very few factors. On the other hand, the strategy of Proof 2 is general. Try solving the problem using the quadratic equation method.</p> <h2 id="quadratic-residue-kick">Quadratic residue kick</h2> <p>Next, I will show you another kick that uses quadratic residues. Watch closely.</p> <blockquote> <p>(Croatian MO 2009) Find all positive integers $m, n$ such that $6^m+2^n+2$ is a perfect square.</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof:</em> We claim the only solution is $m=1,n=3.$ Let $N = 6^m+2^n+2=2(2^{m-1}3^m+2^{n-1}+1)$ be a perfect square. Since $N$ is even, if it is a square, then 4 should divide $N$. This means $2^{m-1}3^m+2^{n-1}+1$ is even. Since the expression is odd if $m,n&gt;1$, we must have $m=1$ or $n=1$.</p> <p><em>Case 1:</em> In this case we consider $m=1$. This condition reduces to finding $n$ so that $N=2^{n} + 8$ is a perfect square. We know that the quadratic residues modulo 16 are only $0,1,4,9$. But if $n &gt; 3$, then $N \equiv 8 \mod 16$ , so it cannot be a perfect square. So n can only be 1,2 or 3. Trying each of the cases, we get N as $10,12,16$. Thus $(m,n) = (1,3)$ is the only solution in this case.</p> <p><em>Case 2:</em> In this case we consider $n=1$. This condition reduces to finding $m$ so that $N=6^{m} +4$ is a perfect square. We know that the quadratic residues modulo $7$ are only $0,1,4,9$. So \[N = 6^m + 4 \equiv (-1)^m + 4 \equiv 5,3 \mod 7.\] Since neither are quadratic residues, we are done.</p> <hr/> <p>Let me present an opportunity to practice all the kicks you have learned</p> <h2 id="practice-your-kicks">Practice your kicks</h2> <ol> <li>(Kurschak MC 1953) Let n be a positive integer, and let $d$ be a positive divisor of $2n^2$. Prove that $n^2+d$ is not a perfect square. (Hint: bounding between consecutive squares.)</li> <li>(RMO 2012) Find all positive integers $n$ such that $3^{2n} +3n^2 +7$ is a perfect square. (Hint: Bound it between consecutive squares. $2$ is the only solution)</li> <li>(Polish MO 2000) Let $m, n$ be positive integers such that $m^2+n^2+m$ is divisible by $mn$. Prove that $m$ is a perfect square. (Hint: Use quadratic equation and focus on the discriminant.)</li> <li>(CRMO 2001) Find all primes $p$ and $q$ such that $p^2 + 7pq + q^2$ is the square of an integer. (Hint: Complete squares and factorize. If $p \neq q$, then $\{3,11\}$ is the other solution.)</li> <li>(Iranian MO 2011). Integers $a, b$ satisfy $a&gt;b$. Also $ab-1, a+b$ are relatively prime and $ab+1, a-b$ are relatively prime. Prove that $(a+b)^2+(ab-1)^2$ is not a perfect square. (Hint: Decompose expression into co-prime factors.)</li> <li>(Australian MO 2002) Find all prime numbers $p, q, r$ such that \[p^q+p^r\] is a perfect square. (Hint: factor out a power of p and note that we have product of relatively prime numbers is a perfect square except one pesky case.)</li> <li>{Harder} (BMO 1994) Find the first number $n$ such that the average of the sum of the squares from $1$ to $𝑛$ (where $𝑛&gt;1$) is a perfect square. (Ans: $337$)</li> <li>(US TST 2008) Let $n$ be a positive integer. Prove that $n^7+7$ is not a perfect square. (looks hard, didnt try much. Let me know if you get this in the comments.)</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="teaching"/><category term="perfect-square"/><category term="number_theory"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Standard problems in olympiads]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Number theory practice for RMO 2024</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Number-theory-Problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Number theory practice for RMO 2024"/><published>2024-10-07T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Number-theory-Problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Number-theory-Problems/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>(BMO R1 2009) Find all integers $x,y,z$ such that \[x^2 + y^2 + z^2 =2(yz+1)\] \[x+y+z=4018.\]</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof</em>: The first equation can be written as $x^2 + (y-z)^2=2.$ So $x = \pm 1, (y-z)=\pm 1.$ So we have four possibilities:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th>\[(y-z)=1\]</th> <th>\[(y-z)=-1\]</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">\[x=1\]</td> <td>\[y+z=4017,y-z=1\]</td> <td>\[y+z=4017,y-z=-1\]</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">\[x=-1\]</td> <td>\[y+z=4019,y-z=1\]</td> <td>\[y+z=4019,y-z=-1\]</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Solving the four equations (by adding and subtracting), we get the solution set for (x,y,z) as ${(1,2009,2008),(-1,2010,2009),(-1,2009,2010),(1,2008,2009)}$.</p> <hr/> <p>(RMO 2002) Find all integers a, b, c, d satisfying the following relations: 1. $1\leq a\leq b\leq c\leq d$ 2. $ab+cd=a+b+c+d+3.$ <em>Proof</em>: Writing the second equation as \((a-1)(b-1)+(c-1)(d-1)=5.\) From the first relation, we see that $0 \leq (a-1)(b-1) \leq (c-1)(d-1)$. Thus we have three cases according to the partition of 5 as $0+5,1+4,2+3$: <strong>Case 1:</strong> $(a-1)(b-1)=0, (c-1)(d-1)=5.$ The first relation forces $a=1$, and $c=2,d=6$, $b=1$ or $2$. So the possible solutions in this case are $(1,1,2,6),(1,2,2,6).$ <strong>Case 2:</strong> $(a-1)(b-1)=1, (c-1)(d-1)=4.$ The second equation can be factored in two ways 2 x 2 and 1 x 4. The first relation forces $a=2,b=2$, and $c=2,d=5$ or $c=d=3$. So the possible solutions in this case are $(2,2,2,5),(2,2,3,3).$ <strong>Case 3:</strong> $(a-1)(b-1)=2, (c-1)(d-1)=3.$ <del>No solution because relation 1 fails.</del></p> <hr/> <p>(RMO 2013) Prove that there do not exist natural numbers $x$ and $y$ , with $x&gt;1$ , such that \(\dfrac{x^7 −1}{x-1} = y^5 +1.\) <em>Proof:</em> Rearranging we get \(\dfrac{x^7-x}{x-1}=y^5.\) Simplifying the expression we get \(x(x^2+x+1)(x^3+1)=y^5.\)</p> \[\begin{eqnarray} (x^2+x+1,x^3+1) &amp;= (x^2+x+1,x^3+1-x(x^2+x+1))\\ &amp;= (x^2+x+1,1-x^2-x)\\ &amp;= (x^2+x+1,2) \in \{1,2\} \end{eqnarray}\] <p>We see that if x is even, then both $x^2+x+1,x^3+1$ are odd. If x is odd, then exactly one of them is even. At any rate, both are not even and thus $(x^2+x+1,x^3+1) = 1$. Clearly, $(x,x^2+x+1)=1, (x,x^3+1)=1$. Thus a product of three numbers, that are pairwise coprime, is a fifth power. <strong>Fact:</strong> If a perfect $n$th power can be factored into pairwise coprime numbers, then the factors themselves are perfect $n$th powers. From the fact and our claims above we see that $x,x^2+x+1,x^3+1$ are perfect fifth powers. So $x=z^5, x^2+x+1=u^5, x^3+1=v^5$ and thus $(z^3)^5 + 1 = v^5$ . Now $x&gt; 1$, and thus we have $z^3&gt; 1,$ so no there is no solution since there are no consecutive fifth powers of natural numbers.</p> <p>For $n &gt; 1$, the the only integer solutions of $a^n = b^n +1$ is $b=0,a=1$ and when n is odd $b=-1,a=0$ .<br/> <em>Proof:</em> We prove the claim by case analysis: <strong>Case 1:</strong> First we assume a,b are non-negative integers. Note that $a&gt;b$ . Since $a-b$ divides $a^n - b^n$, we conclude $a-b=1$. Plugging in $a=b+1$, we get \(\sum_{k=1}^{n-1}\binom{n}{k}b^k = 0.\) Thus $b=0,a=1.$<br/> <strong>Case 2:</strong> Now if $a,b$ are non-positive, then set $a=-u, b=-v$ so that $u,v$ are non-negative. Now if n is odd we see that \(-u^n = -v^n + 1 \implies v^n = u^n+1.\) So we are in Case 1 and thus $u=0$ and $v=1$. Therefore $a=0, b=-1$.</p> <hr/> <p>(BMO R1 2015) A positive integer is called <em>charming</em> if it is equal to 2 or is of the form $3^i 5^j$ where i and j are non-negative integers. Prove that every positive integer can be written as a sum of different charming integers.</p> <p>We need the following lemma <strong>Lemma:</strong> For any positive integer $n &gt; 2$ there exists $i,j &gt; 0$ such that \(3^i 5^j \leq n &lt; 2 (3^i 5^j).\)<em>Proof:</em> We proceed by contradiction. Suppose the given statement is false, i.e. There exists positive integer n &gt; 2, for all $i,j &gt;0$ such that $2(3^i5^j) \leq n$ or $n &lt; 3^i5^j$. Choose $i_0,j_0$ such that $3^{i_0}5^{j_0} &lt; n$ and is the largest such. For our $i_0,j_0$, we have $2(3^{i_0}5^{j_0}) \leq n.$</p> <p>This means there is an positive integer $n&gt;2$ such that $2 (3^{i_0} 5^{j_0}) \leq n &lt; 3^{i_0+1}5^{j_0},$ for any $i,j$. If $j&gt;0$, then we claim \(3^{i+2}5^{j-1} &lt; n &lt; 2(3^{i+2}5^{j-1})\) $3^{i+2}5^{j-1} &lt; 2(3^i5^j)\leq n &lt; 3^{i+1}5^j &lt; 2(3^{i+2}5^{j-1}).$ So $i &gt; 0$, <del>a similar proof can be given.</del> $\blacksquare$</p> <p><em>Proof:</em> We proceed by strong induction. Let P(n) denote the proposition: “The number n can be written as a sum of different charming integers.” <strong>Base case:</strong> P(1) is true since $1= 3^0$. <strong>Strong induction hypothesis:</strong> $P(n)$ is true for all $n &lt; k$. <strong>Strong induction claim:</strong> $P(k)$ is true. <em>Proof:</em> First we note that $P(2)$ is true since 2 is given to be charming. For k&gt; 2, the lemma states that there exists $i,j &gt; 0$ such that \(3^i 5^j \leq k &lt; 2 (3^i 5^j).\) Let $m = k - 3^i5^j$ and thus $0 \leq m &lt; 3^i5^j$. Since $m &lt; 3^i 5^j \leq k$, we have $m &lt; k.$ If $m=0$, then $k=3^i5^j$ and thus k is charming. So $P(k)$ is true. On the other hand if $k &gt; m &gt; 0$, from strong induction claim, we have m is a sum of different charming numbers. Since $m &lt; 3^i5^j$, the number $3^i5^j$ cannot appear in any decomposition of m into different charming numbers. Therefore if we replace $m$ by sum of any set of charming numbers \(k = m + 3^i5^j\) then k is a sum of different charming numbers.</p> <p>240 = c + (240-c). If we choose largest possible c, then perhaps c &gt; 240 -c =&gt; 2c &gt; 240 &gt; c &lt;=&gt; c&lt; 240 &lt; 2c</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="solving"/><category term="Olympiad"/><category term="Diophantine-equations"/><category term="number_theory"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Miscellaneous problems from RMO and BMO]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Combinatorics Configuration problems from BMO and RMO</title><link href="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Combinatorics-Problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combinatorics Configuration problems from BMO and RMO"/><published>2024-10-07T15:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T15:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Combinatorics-Problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srikanthbpai.github.io/blog/2024/Combinatorics-Problems/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p><strong>A 6 x 6 square is dissected into nine rectangles by lines parallel to its side such that all these rectangles have integer sides. Prove that there are always two congruent rectangles.</strong></p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof:</em> We proceed by contradiction. If the square can be dissected into nine non-congruent rectangles, we will show that the total area will exceed 36.</p> <p>We will enumerate the areas of non-congruent rectangles with sidelengths of at most 6 units and the number of such non-congruent rectangles.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center">Area</th> <th style="text-align: center">a x b</th> <th style="text-align: center">number</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> <td style="text-align: center">1 x 1</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> <td style="text-align: center">1 x 2</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">3</td> <td style="text-align: center">1 x 3</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">4</td> <td style="text-align: center">1 x 4, 2 x 2</td> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">5</td> <td style="text-align: center">1 x 5</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">6</td> <td style="text-align: center">1x 6, 2 x 3</td> <td style="text-align: center">2</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">8</td> <td style="text-align: center">2 x 4</td> <td style="text-align: center">1</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Total sum of areas of 9 rectangles $\geq$ 1 + 2+ 3+4 +4 + 5 +6 +6 +8 = 39 This means that any dissection of a 6 x 6 square into 9 incongruent rectangles has atleast 39 sq units as area. But 6x6 square has area 36. So this is the required contradiction.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p><strong>The numbers 1, 2, 3, . . . , n are arranged in a particular order. One can swap any two adjacent numbers. Prove that after performing an odd number of such operations, the arrangement of the numbers thus obtained will differ from the original one.</strong></p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof:</em></p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p><strong>A teacher wrote the quadratic $x^2 +10x+20$ on the board. Then, each student either increased by $1$ or decreased by $1$ either the constant or the linear coefficient. Finally $x^2 +20x+10$ appeared. Did a quadratic expression with integer zeros necessarily appear on the board in the process?</strong></p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof:</em> (sketch) Represent the polynomial $x^2+ax+b$ on the plane by the point $(a,b)$. students moves will create a path out of lattice points. Now the family of polynomials $x^2 + (n+1)x + n$ is represented by the set of lattice points on the line y=x-1. Since the starting and ending points lie on the either side, the path must cross the polynomial $x^2 + (n+1)x + n$ which has integer roots.</p> <hr/> <blockquote> <p>(BMO R2 2016) <strong>Naomi and Tom play a game, with Naomi going first. They take it in turns to pick an integer from 1 to 100, each time selecting an integer which no-one has chosen before. A player loses the game if, after their turn, the sum of all the integers chosen since the start of the game (by both of them) cannot be written as the difference of two square numbers. Determine if one of the players has a winning strategy, and if so, which.</strong></p> </blockquote> <p><em>Proof:</em> I claim Naomi has a winning strategy. First we note that n cannot be written as difference of two squares iff $n \equiv 2 \mod 4$ . Twenty-five numbers from 1 to 100 are in each remainder class modulo 4. Naomi’s strategy is to maintain the sum of the picked numbers as a multiple of 4, forcing Tom to pick a number congruent to 2 mod 4 eventually. She can implement the strategy by the following procedure:</p> <ul> <li>Start with a 4</li> <li>If tom picks 1 mod 4, then choose a number that is 3 mod 4 number and vice versa.</li> <li>If tom picks a multiple of 4, then write a multiple of 4. Naomi can always run her strategy because of the following reasons:</li> <li>Since there are odd number of multiples of 4, she will always be the last one to write a multiple of 4.</li> <li>Since there are equal numbers of 1 and 3 mod 4 numbers and she never starts with one of them, she will be the last one to write 1 or 3. Since she never has to write a 2 mod 4, she wins.</li> </ul> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Olympiad,"/><category term="solving"/><category term="invariant"/><category term="monovariant"/><category term="combinatorics"/><category term="Olympiad"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A 6 x 6 square is dissected into nine rectangles by lines parallel to its side such that all these rectangles have integer sides. Prove that there are always two congruent rectangles.]]></summary></entry></feed>